<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Christian plea for Christians baptisme: raised from the grave of apostasie. or, a short treatise, being a reproof of some things written by A. R. in his treatise, intituled, The vanitie of childish baptisme. In the answer whereof, the lawfulnesse of infants baptisme is defended, the sufficiency of our baptisme received in the state of apostasie, shewed: and the deficiencie of the arguments brought against it manifested, by sufficient grounds and reasons drawn from the sweet fountains of holy Scripture. / [by] S.C.</title>
            <author>Chidley, Samuel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 118 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79488</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3836</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E104_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12174</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859230</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859230</idno>
            <idno type="VID">155922</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79488)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 155922)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 18:E104[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Christian plea for Christians baptisme: raised from the grave of apostasie. or, a short treatise, being a reproof of some things written by A. R. in his treatise, intituled, The vanitie of childish baptisme. In the answer whereof, the lawfulnesse of infants baptisme is defended, the sufficiency of our baptisme received in the state of apostasie, shewed: and the deficiencie of the arguments brought against it manifested, by sufficient grounds and reasons drawn from the sweet fountains of holy Scripture. / [by] S.C.</title>
                  <author>Chidley, Samuel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 30, [2]p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. P. and M. S. and to be sold by Ben. Allen in Popes-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"A. R." = Andrew Ritor.</note>
                  <note>S. C. = Samuel Chidley.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 25th"; "hidley" is inserted following 'S. C.'.</note>
                  <note>A reply to: Ritor, Anddrew. Treatise of the vanity of childish baptisme.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ritor, Andrew. --  Treatise of the vanity of childish baptisme.</term>
               <term>Infant baptism. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:155922:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A CHRISTIAN PLEA FOR CHRISTIANS BAPTISME: Raiſed from the grave of <hi>Apoſtaſie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>OR,</hi> A SHORT TREATISE, Being a reproof of ſome things written by <hi>A. R.</hi> in his Treatiſe, intituled, The vanitie of Childiſh Baptiſme.</p>
            <p>In the Anſwer whereof, The lawfulneſſe of Infants Baptiſme is defended, the ſufficiency of our Baptiſme received in the ſtate of <hi>Apoſtaſie,</hi> ſhewed: and <hi>the deficiencie of the Arguments brought againſt it</hi> mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted, by ſufficient grounds and reaſons drawn from the ſweet fountains of holy Scripture.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>S. C.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Ezek. 37.12, 13, 14.</hi>
                  </bibl> O my people, I will open your graves, and cauſe you to come up out of your graves, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2. Chron. 30.18 19.</hi>
                  </bibl> The good Lord pardon every one that prepareth his heart to ſeek God, the Lord God of his fathers, though he be not cleanſed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the purification of the ſanctuary.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Jer. 9.25.26.</hi>
                  </bibl> Behold, the daies come, ſaith the Lord, that I will puniſh all them which are circumciſed, with the uncircumciſed. Egypt, and Judah, and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and the children of Ammon, and Moab, and all that are cut off into corners, that dwell in the wilderneſſe: for all theſe Nations are uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, and all the houſe of Iſrael are uncircumciſed in the heart.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Rev. 11.1, 2.</hi>
                  </bibl> And there was given me a reed like unto a rod, and the Angel ſtood, ſaying, Riſe and meaſure the Temple of God, and the Altar, and them that worſhip therein. But the Court which is without the Temple caſt out, and meaſure it not: for it is given unto the Gentiles, &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>T. P.</hi> and <hi>M. S.</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Ben. Allen</hi> in Popes-head-Alley. 1643.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:155922:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:155922:2"/>
            <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER, Grace, Mercie, and Peace be multiplyed, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving conſidered, that the weakneſſe, and frivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſneſſe, of the Arguments brought by <hi>A. R.</hi> againſt Baptiſme, deſerved no Anſwer; and conceiving that moſt of them were publickly confuted in print<note n="*" place="margin">By <hi>Ainſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth, Wilkin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Clif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binſon,</hi> &amp; divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</note>, before any of them were thus publiſhed, I thought not to have medled with them in ſuch a publick way.</p>
            <p>But further conſidering, that the ſaid Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of his, were divulged in print, and might do much hurt amongſt ſome ignorant people, <hi>who would do better if they knew better;</hi> I thought it meet to help to take off this new vizard, put upon the Anabaptiſts old out-worn arguments, and ſo to pull down this little tottering turret of Babel; becauſe that in this falſe fire, and light of the ſparks of theſe crackling thornes, the makers thereof delight ſtill to walke, and ſome are yet deluded, by ſuch frothie Divinitie, and ſmokie clouds of ſubl me ſophiſtry; without due triall of them, by the light of Gods Word; or weighing them in the balance of the Sanctuary.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, in obedience to God, and love to his people; I have here un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken to uſe my talent in vindicating the lawfulneſſe of <hi>Chriſtians Baptiſme,</hi> raiſed with them out of the <hi>grave</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtaſie</hi> of the <hi>man</hi> of <hi>ſinne,</hi> which hath been for many yeers, in which Apoſtate eſtate, and wretched condition, the name of God hath been greatly profained, his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions (though not deſtroyed) yet highly abuſed, to the deſtruction of many ſouls; out of which ſtate, God hath called ſome, who have obeyed his voyce, and come out of <hi>Babel</hi> to <hi>Sion;</hi> and are as dearly beloved of God, as the penitent <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> whom God in former time brought from <hi>Jeroboams apoſtaſie</hi> to <hi>Judah,</hi> where they kept the feaſt, unto the Lord, and were both <hi>young,</hi> and <hi>old,</hi> accepted of him, though they retained the <hi>Circumciſion</hi> which they received in that apoſtate eſtate, where there was neither <hi>true viſible Church, miniſtry, worſhip, nor government,</hi> but all <hi>diabolicall,</hi> and <hi>Apoſtaticall:</hi> yet (God having reſerved his own ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance pure unto himſelf) the evill of the manner being repented of, by them;
<pb facs="tcp:155922:3"/> the thing it ſelf was not commanded to be adminiſtred upon them again.</p>
            <p>And ſurely, God could have commanded that Circum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſion [done in Apoſtaſie, by a wrong adminiſtrator, and by a falſe power, and upon a wrong ſubject,] to have been eſteemed as not done at all, and that the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties when they returned from that <hi>Apoſtaſie,</hi> ſhould have been <hi>circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed</hi> again; but he would not, no more hath he commanded us to be <hi>bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed</hi> again, though we were <hi>baptiſed</hi> in an <hi>Apoſtate ſtate:</hi> for <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme</hi> is as durable as <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> and God is as able to purge <hi>bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme</hi> now, as he was to purge <hi>Circumciſion</hi> then.</p>
            <p>But Mr. <hi>A. R.</hi> hath taken upon him to prove the <hi>Baptiſme</hi> which we Chriſtians received (in the ſtate of <hi>Apoſtaſie</hi>) to be none of <hi>Gods Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme;</hi> but <hi>inſufficient;</hi> In the proſecution whereof, he alledgeth ſeverall <hi>particulars,</hi> by which he would diſprove the ſame: which <hi>particulars</hi> are examined, and his inferences from thence anſwered in the enſuing diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>But it would not have been amiſſe, if he had well conſidered (for abridgement of his work) that <hi>baptiſme,</hi> being (by his own confeſſion) a <hi>great</hi> ordinance of the <hi>New Teſtament;</hi> To make it leſſe generall, or leſſe durable then <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> or inferiour thereunto, would be to make Chriſt leſſe faithfull in his houſe then <hi>Moſes;</hi> and inferiour to him: But <hi>baptiſme</hi> is more generall then <hi>Circumciſion:</hi> And <hi>Chriſt</hi> is more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent then <hi>Moſes, and Baptiſme is as durable as Circumciſion.</hi> Therefore ſeeing Circumciſion was not worne out by thoſe; Baptiſme is not worne out by theſe.</p>
            <p>Think not (Chriſtian Reader) that I intend to plead for the Apoſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or any of her daughters, or for their <hi>miniſtry, worſhip,</hi> or <hi>Government!</hi> So farre am I from this, that I utterly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce, and diſclaime the ſame; and leave the Juſtification of them to the diſpoſition of thoſe who account them no worſe then <hi>Heathens</hi> that never knew the truth; and ſeek to leſſen their ſinne by labouring to vindicate their ſuppoſed innocencie, teaching them [in this] to plead <hi>ignoramus,</hi> and not guiltie, when they are juſtly accuſed for committing of <hi>ſacriledge.</hi> Yea, and <hi>Gods</hi> definitive ſentence pronounced againſt them, and his just judgements executed (and daily executing) upon them, as appeareth at this very day, ſince the ſharp arrows of the <hi>Almighty</hi> have been (and are ſtill) ſo generally ſcattered abroad, to the deſtruction, and ruination of thoſe perſons; not onely for their abuſe of common meats, and drinks, and other temporall bleſſings; but chiefly (and above all) for the abuſe and prophanation of ſpirituall things, as (the prophanation of) Gods holy word, and ordinances, which they diſtribute to all ſorts of ſinners that come under
<pb facs="tcp:155922:3"/> the notion of a verball profeſſion, though very vile in their life and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation. All which is of us not to be leſſened, or excuſed, as if it were not <hi>ſacriledge</hi> (or theft in an high degree) but rather to be lamented, that thoſe perſons who draw neer unto God with their mouthes, and outwardly pretend to ſtand for Chriſt, and fight for his true Religion; (taking upon them to defend the ſame, ſome with the Word, others with the ſword) againſt thoſe who do oppoſe them) ſhould have their hearts ſo farre aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from God, as ſo much to take his holy Name in vaine, and prophane his Sabbaths, as thoſe do who on that day powre out their meat-offerings and drink-offerings, in the idolatrous high places, which being a defilement unto the Land, are by the laws of God deſtinated to deſtruction. For theſe and the like abominations (I ſay) we ought to mourne<note n="*" place="margin">Ezek. 9.</note>: and that they ſhould ſo ſteal his ordinances, and abuſe his Word, to the deſtruction and ruination, ſpuing, and rooting out of themſelves, and their poſteritie, from thoſe good and fruitfull lands wherein God of his mercie had planted them.</p>
            <p>Theſe and the like evils, were the cauſes why God did bring upon his people Iſrael of old, divers heavie and ſore judgements, as peſtilence, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, and ſword, and wilde beaſts to devoure both them and theirs, yea though they were <hi>circumciſed in fleſh,</hi> yet becauſe they were not <hi>circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in heart,</hi> God threatned to viſit them with the <hi>uncircumciſed in fleſh</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Jer. 9.25, 26.</note>, <hi>and make their Cities deſolate without inhabitants, and their houſes without man and their land utterly deſolate: and that he would remove them farre away,</hi> and never promiſed to bring them againe from captivitie, nor propheſied good unto any but thoſe who were upright in heart; <hi>even the tenth part,</hi> (or rather leſſe) which were <hi>the holy ſeed, the ſubſtance</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Iſa 6.11, 12, 13.</note>, <hi>and the remnant</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Cap 10.21.</note>.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, it evidently appeareth, that in an idolatrous eſtate, and Apoſtate condition, there is no true comfort, or conſolation to be expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; though they have and enjoy <hi>baptiſme</hi> as of old the <hi>Jewiſh Apoſtates</hi> had, and did enjoy <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> but as theſe are ſinners in like <hi>manner</hi> as thoſe were; ſo theſe may expect the ſame <hi>meaſure</hi> of puniſhment (from the hand of God) as thoſe had: yea, conſidering that theſe have their own actuall ſins, lying upon them<note n="d" place="margin">Rev. 9.18.20, 21. Rev. 18.24.</note>; and the ſinnes of the wicked Jews both active and imputative, ſtatively imputed unto them<note n="e" place="margin">Mat. 23.34, 35, 36.32.33. Rev. 11.8.</note>: It ſhould make them to tremble at the Word of God, which muſt be fulfilled, which hath decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>that judgements are prepared for ſcorners</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Prov. 19.29.</note>; and that <hi>the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the wickeds cup, ſhall be ſnares, fire and brimſtone, burning ſtormes and tempeſts</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 11.6.</note>: <hi>and that hell hath enlarged her ſelf, and
<pb facs="tcp:155922:4"/> opened her mouth without meaſure; and that their glory, and their multitude, and their pomp, and he that rejoyceth ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend into it</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Iſa. 5.14.</note>.</p>
            <p>But as the Lord hath called us out of the ſinke of Sodome, and grave of Babyloniſh and Aegyptian Apoſtaſie (where our Lord was crucified;) ſo we muſt not diſhonour him ſo farre as to caſt away his holy veſſels, or any good thing of his which we have received; for God is able to purge thoſe things which are his own; upon our repentance; So that the evill manner of receiving <hi>Baptiſme</hi> doth not argue but that the thing in it ſelf is good, and may be applyed to the ſame end and uſe for which it was firſt given. Therefore as we are come out of <hi>Babel,</hi> ſo let us labour to imitate <hi>Sion,</hi> ſet forth unto us in the Scriptures; which doth teach us not to lay againe the foundation, but to go on unto perfection<note n="i" place="margin">Heb. 6.1, 2.</note>, [even as the children of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael did when they went up from <hi>Jeroboams apoſtaſie,</hi> to keep the feast in <hi>Judah;</hi>] and not (Babel-like) confound both our ſelves and others, as thoſe do, who deny, and diſclaime the ordinance of <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> which they have received in <hi>Apoſtaſie;</hi> which <hi>Baptiſme</hi> they conceive to be no more then a naturall, or morall act, and not a divine ordinance: thinking to take more advantage againſt the ſame, in the proſecution of it, then is given them either from their doctrine, or practiſe, or any rule revealed in Gods Word.</p>
            <p>Yea, they entangle themſelves ſo in the bryars, and thornes of the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe (not knowing by their own grounds which way, or how to take up baptiſme) that they are driven now to hold a Church all of unbaptized perſons; and that though none of them be baptiſed, yet the ſaid Church may ſet apart one or more of her unbaptized members, and give them au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie to baptize themſelves and others<note n="*" place="margin">For this ſee Mr. <hi>Spilſbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſme, <hi>p.</hi> 38 li. 7.8. 9. 10. lin. 33. to li. 40. <hi>p.</hi> 39. lin. 31.33.</note>; and yet they grant that bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme may be where there is no Church, and ſo (caſting away the baptiſme which they formerly received) they are driven (in taking up their new <hi>bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme</hi>) to affirm that an unbaptiſed perſon or perſons may and muſt baptiſe themſelves, and after that baptize others, elſe true baptiſme can never be had: but I wiſh they would apply the counſell to themſelves which they give unto others not to depend upon humaine and unwritten traditions, but upon the Word of God, which is the onely rule for every divine action. Here you ſee after what manner they lay down, and take up baptiſme. But,</p>
            <p>Touching Mr. <hi>A. R.</hi> his manner of baptizing, he doth not tell us in particular, but in generall, he ſaith, <hi>Men and women muſt be dipt;</hi> he doth not declare the particular manner how they muſt be dipt, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth that; which thing would be known: In the meane time ſeeing this
<pb facs="tcp:155922:4"/> ſubject by way of anſwer and oppoſition to them is treated on, by divers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; amongſt whom, one of them is a Poet of their own<note n="*" place="margin">M. <hi>Fleet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood</hi> againſt dipping.</note>, I inſiſt not much thereon.</p>
            <p>In bringing his laſt particular (concerning the ſubjects of baptiſme) he ſhooteth ſo awry that he miſſeth the marke, and doth not ſpeak clear out: for he ſpeaketh of <hi>Infants</hi> in generall, without putting a diſtinction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Infants</hi> of <hi>Idolaters, and</hi> the <hi>Infants</hi> of true <hi>Chriſtians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By which it appeareth (as alſo by the reſt of his words touching this matter) that he judgeth all Infants to be in one viſible eſtate, which to think is very erronious.</p>
            <p>If God had commanded the <hi>Infants</hi> of <hi>Idolaters</hi> to be <hi>circumciſed,</hi> as he commanded the <hi>infants</hi> of the faithfull <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>proſolites.</hi> And<note n="a" place="margin">Exod. 12.48.</note> if God in <hi>baptizing</hi> the <hi>Iſraelites infants</hi> in the <hi>Red ſea</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">1 Cor. 10 1.2. Pſal. 77.16.17.19.20.</note>, had bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed an Infant of wicked parents; if God had deſtroyed the infants of <hi>Abraham</hi> with the infants of Sodome<note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 18.24.</note>, and the infants of Iſrael with the infants of Egypt<note n="d" place="margin">Exod. 12.29.</note> in that extraordinarie way: we might have thought the infants of Idolaters and the infants of true Chriſtians to be all in one viſible eſtate; But God commanded no infants to be circumciſed but thoſe which were in Covenant with him<note n="e" place="margin">Gen. 17.14.</note>, neither did he baptize any other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, but put a difference between the holy and prophane, both by his words and actions<note n="f" place="margin">Gen. 18.17.19 20.25 32. Cap. 19.12.13. Exod 12.26.27.29. Joſh. 1.13.14. 1 Sam. 15.3.</note>. Therefore we have no warrant to judge both <hi>infants</hi> of <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers</hi> and the <hi>infants</hi> of <hi>unbeleevers</hi> to be all in one <hi>viſible</hi> eſtate. For though God <hi>viſiteth the iniquities of the fathers upon the children to the third and fourth generation of thoſe that hate him; yet he ſheweth mercie to thouſands of thoſe that love him, and keep his Commandments</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Ver. 6.</note>.</p>
            <p>The deniall of <hi>Baptiſme</hi> to the infants of beleevers ariſeth from many groſſe and ignorant miſtakes of the true ſence and meanin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of many texts of Scriptures, as alſo from many fooliſh conceptions and idle dream<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, wherewith perſons have intoxicated their minds, and wraped themſelves into grievous abſurdities. As in other things they bewray a great deale of ignorance, ſo do they in this about infants, and are driven (in maintenance of this errour) to diſcover more errours in themſelves,<note n="g" place="margin">Exod. 20.5.</note> and to ſtrike at the fundamentall principles of Religion.</p>
            <p>They ſuppoſe that thoſe Scriptures which ſet forth the excellent privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of the <hi>faithfull</hi> and <hi>their ſeed,</hi> concerne not <hi>infants</hi> at all, but only perſons of yeers that are capable, and do profeſſe faith, and repentance; limiting the ſeed to them of yeers onely: or to Chriſts perſon, barring <hi>out infants</hi> in their conceptions from <hi>viſible</hi> union and communion with him.</p>
            <p>Where it is ſaid that the <hi>Covenant</hi> of <hi>Circumciſion</hi> was to be in
<pb facs="tcp:155922:5"/> 
               <hi>their fleſh</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 17.13.</note>, they interpret that <hi>fleſh</hi> to be <hi>Chriſt,</hi> where Circumciſion in Scripture is called <hi>the ſigne</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Gen 17.11.</note> 
               <hi>and ſeal of the righteouſneſſe of faith</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 4.11.</note>, they limit that to <hi>Abraham</hi> onely, and <hi>Gen 17.10.</hi> (theſe words) this is my Covenant<note n="*" place="margin">For this ſee <hi>A. R.</hi> his ſecond book. pa. 24 lin 13. 14.</note>, they take literally to be a reall Covenant, without taking the expoſition, verſ. <hi>11.</hi> even as the Papiſts expound <hi>Matth. 26.26</hi> This is my body, for his reall and corporall preſence. They alſo would (moſt abſurdly) make <hi>Baptiſme leſſe general,</hi> and <hi>more generall</hi> then <hi>circumciſion,</hi> which implyeth a flat contradiction.</p>
            <p>Whereas it is ſaid, <hi>He that beleeveth, and is baptiſed, ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, &amp;c.</hi> This they ſay cannot be applyed to any infants; for, ſay they, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants have no faith either by action, or imputation: then they are driven forcibly to run upon another abſurditie, that either <hi>Infants are ſaved without faith,</hi> ar elſe that they are not ſaved at all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Circumciſion</hi> they conceive was not a ſeale of the <hi>new</hi> Covenant; but of ſome <hi>carnall</hi> thing; but this is a <hi>carnall</hi> affirmation, like the judgement of him that ſaith, the Church of the <hi>Jews</hi> was conſtituted upon <hi>nature,</hi> and <hi>carnalitie; oppoſite to the ſpirit,</hi> and farre different from the Churches of Chriſt<note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 22.17.18.19.20.</note>.</p>
            <p>Theſe abſurdities with many more, follow one another like links of one chain; yea this is an evill under the Sun, that thoſe things which are <hi>old er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors,</hi> by ſome now adayes are eſteemed as <hi>new truths.</hi> Amongſt whom ſome there are in particular, who deny the heavenly ſtate, and baptiſme of holy infants, and alſo the baptiſme of Chriſt received in the ſtate of apoſtaſie, not diſtinguiſhing between a thing well done, ill done, and not done at all: which diſtinctions ought to be obſerved, both in ſpirituall and temporall things.</p>
            <p>And conſidering (Chriſtian Reader) that in many things we ſin all, and are ſubject to erre in our beſt actions, I earneſtly deſire thee to take nothing upon truſt, which I ſet down, but duely trie, and diſcreetly weigh the ſame in the balance of the Lords ſanctuary; and if thou reap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit by my poore endeavours, give the glory to God: and wherin I miſſe it, let me be informed, that the ſame may (by me) be reformed; for the unchangeable truth of Jeſus Chriſt we ought to love dearly, prize highly; and purchaſe it without ever parting from it, and cheriſh it, as the Lord doth put it into our boſome, and ſo become one with it, even like unto Jeſus Chriſt who is the way, the truth, the life, and the light of thoſe who in his light do ſee light; whoſe unſearchable riches I deſire with all Saints, every way to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend: and therewith bid thee farewell. And ſo remain,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy Chriſtian Brother in the fellowſhip of the Goſpel, <hi>S C.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:155922:5"/>
            <head>A REPROOF OF SOME things written by <hi>A.R.</hi> in his Treatiſe intituled, <hi>The vanitie of Childiſh Baptiſme.</hi> In the Anſwer whereof, The lawfulneſſe of Infants Baptiſme is defended, the <hi>ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciencie of our Baptiſme received in the ſtate of Apoſtaſie ſhewed,</hi> and the deficiencie of the Arguments brought againſt it manifeſted by ſufficient grounds and reaſons, drawn from the ſweet fountains of holy Scripture.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Mr. AR.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOu have (in your title page and Epiſtle to the Reader) taken up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you to do that which you are not able; and promiſed that which you cannot perform, and affirmed that which you cannot prove, by Scripture: which is, that <hi>the Baptiſme of Infants is unwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable, and a meer device, brought into the world for politick and by ends, &amp;c.</hi> and that therefore (it being the baptiſme in the Church of England) you have undertaken to prove it to be deficient, and none of Gods Baptiſme.</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the entrance of your diſcourſe you confeſſe,<note place="margin">Pag. 1.</note> 
               <hi>That Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme is a great ordinance of the new Teſtament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I adde, that though every ordinance of the new Teſtament be great, yet there is a difference between them; for ſome ordinances are <hi>active</hi> (both in reſpect of the adminiſtrator and partaker thereof,) other ordinances are meerly <hi>paſſive</hi> (in reference to the parties upon whom the ſame are adminiſtred) amongſt which paſſive ordinances <hi>Baptiſme</hi> is one<note n="*" place="margin">So Mr. <hi>Spilsbery</hi> ſaith, the ſubject of Baptiſme is to be paſſive: See his Treatiſe, pa. 26. li 7.</note>.</p>
            <p>That <hi>Baptiſme</hi> is ſo (as I have here declared) the Scriptures (<hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38.) which you have quoted, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xpreſſe, where the Apoſtles were commanded to baptiſe others; And the Diſciples are
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:155922:6"/> not bidden by <hi>Peter</hi> to baptiſe themſelves, but to be baptiſed by others. And (you may know that) the <hi>Eunuch baptiſed not (himſelf) but Philip (a baptiſed perſon) baptiſed him:</hi> Act. 8.38. And therefore (in this reſpect) <hi>baptiſme</hi> is unto us, as <hi>circumciſion</hi> was to the Saints of old, (to wit) an ordinance, not <hi>acted</hi> by the <hi>ſubject</hi> (or receiver) but ſubmitted unto,<note place="margin">Joſh. 5.</note> and <hi>ſuffered;</hi> ſo it is ſaid, <hi>Joſhua circumciſed the children of Iſrael the ſecond time, for they were uncircumciſed. God</hi> did not require them to <hi>circumciſe</hi> themſelves, but <hi>Joſhua</hi> (a <hi>circumciſed</hi> perſon) was to <hi>circumciſe</hi> them. <hi>Joſ.</hi> 5.2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8 9.</p>
            <p>And as to <hi>circumciſion</hi> then, there was required, <hi>a right inſtrument, a right ſubject,</hi> and an <hi>enrighting power;</hi> ſo there is now required to <hi>baptiſme.</hi> But as <hi>circumciſion</hi> was <hi>Gods,</hi> though the <hi>ſubject,</hi> and <hi>inſtrument,</hi> and <hi>power</hi> was not right; So is <hi>baptiſme</hi> now <hi>Gods holy inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> though done by <hi>a falſe miniſter,</hi> upon a <hi>falſe ſubject;</hi> and by a <hi>falſe power.</hi> And though theſe <hi>Antichriſtians</hi> have no command (or warrant) from God to <hi>baptiſe</hi> Apoſtates (or any other perſons) no more then the <hi>idolatrous Iſraelites</hi> had to <hi>circumciſe,</hi> yet as that <hi>cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion</hi> then adminiſtred, after that manner (contrary to Gods re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed will) was not changed from being <hi>Gods,</hi> nor done over again, upon thoſe that returned out of that <hi>Apoſtaſie:</hi> So <hi>baptiſme</hi> now though it be adminiſtred by theſe <hi>Apoſtates,</hi> after ſuch an <hi>idolatrous manner,</hi> and upon ſuch <hi>idolatrous ſubjects,</hi> yet it doth not make a nullitie of the ordinance.</p>
            <p>By this it appeareth, that you have laid the ground of your rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning amiſſe (in bringing your five particulars) to make a nullitie of our <hi>baptiſme</hi> which we have received in <hi>Apoſtaſie,</hi> the inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie of which grounds of yours, ſhall be further ſhewed in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of the <hi>particulars</hi> which follow.</p>
            <p>Your firſt particular ground (by which you ſay you will diſprove the baptiſme in the Church of England) is,<note place="margin">Pag. 2.</note> becauſe (as you affirme) that <hi>the end for which baptiſme is there adminiſtred is to regenerate the infants there baptiſed;</hi> for proof whereof you repeat their forme of words before, and after <hi>baptiſme,</hi> [but you mention not the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>inſtitution,</hi> which they pronounce in the act of <hi>baptiſing</hi>] and you would argue that <hi>becauſe they declare that all men be conceived and born in ſinne;</hi> and becauſe they ſay, <hi>that our Saviour Chriſt ſaith, none can enter into the kingdome of God, except he be regenerated, and born anew, of water and the holy Ghoſt: and becauſe the Miniſter beſeecheth the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to call upon God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Father through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that of his
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:155922:6"/> bountifull mercy he will grant to the children that thing which by nature they cannot have, that they may be baptiſed with water, and the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And becauſe the Miniſter and people pray thus <hi>We beſeech thee of thine infinite mercies, that thou wilt mercifully look upon theſe children; ſanctifie them, and waſh them with the holy Ghoſt, that they being deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from thy wrath, may be received into the Ark of Chriſts Church, and being ſtedfaſt in faith, joyfull through hope, and rooted in charitie, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>We call upon thee for theſe infants, that they coming to thy holy bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, may receive the remiſſion of their ſins, by ſpirituall regeneration, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Give thy holy Spirit to theſe infants, that they may be born again, and be made heirs of everlaſting ſalvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo becauſe <hi>the Miniſter (after he hath caſt a little water on the childrens faces openly forthwith, (without bluſhing</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Lin. 28.</note>) <hi>ſaith: Now ſeeing that theſe children be regenerated, and grafted into the body of Chriſts congregation, &amp;c. And then exhorts the people to give thanks to God, for that it hath pleaſed him to regenerate the infants with his holy Spirit, and received them for his own children by adoption, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From theſe premiſes you would infer that the baptiſme is falſe, which ground of yours is very weak; yea the ground of your reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is amiſſe, and contrary to reaſon.</p>
            <p>For it is no right arguing to bring the mixing of their traditions as a nihilation of Gods inſtitution.</p>
            <p>And their confeſſion <hi>that all men be born and conceived in ſin, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition of the words of Chriſt, and the exhortation to call upon God the Father through Jeſus Chriſt, that he will give them that of his mercy which (they confeſſe) by nature they cannot have, that they might be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed with water and the holy Ghoſt.</hi> Doth not argue that the baptiſme is not Gods ordinance, for it is neither their high conceptions, or great eſtimations, or ſuch verball pronuntiations that doth deſtroy or make void Gods holy inſtitutions: yet it is a prophanation of the Name of God, and ſo it is of the ordinance, becauſe the <hi>perſons</hi> who adminiſter the ſame, are <hi>Idolaters,</hi> and the <hi>ſubjects</hi> upon whom it is <hi>adminiſtred,</hi> are the ſeed of <hi>Apoſtates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither is it their beſeeching God of his infinite mercies, <hi>that he will mercifully look upon theſe children, and ſanctifie them, and waſh them with the holy Ghoſt;</hi> that will diſanull the ordinance, and make it of none effect. Neither doth their praying, <hi>that the children may be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from Gods wrath, and that they may be received into the Ark of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:155922:7"/> Chriſts Church, and be ſtedfaſt in faith, joyfull through hope, and rooted in charitie, &amp;c.</hi> overthrow Gods ordinance, and make the Baptiſme received no ordinance of God. Neither doth their acknowledging of baptiſme to be Gods, and to be holy, and there praying for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſins for the Infants by ſpirituall regeneration, (nor their aſcribing regeneration to the holy Spirit) prove the baptiſme there adminiſtred to be no true baptiſme.</p>
            <p>And it is not their <hi>ſprinkling</hi> or caſting water upon the face of the <hi>children</hi> that maketh a nullitie of the ordinance; though he <hi>without bluſhing</hi> ſay afterwards, that the children be regenerated; for whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he bluſh or not bluſh, that is not materiall; to prove the point which you brought it for.</p>
            <p>And though the exhortation which the Miniſter gives to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple together with the reſt <hi>agreeth with their Catechiſe,</hi> the particulars whereof (concerning infants regeneration) though they were confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by theſe Fathers<note n="*" place="margin">Ierome, Auguſtin, Zanchus, Peter Martyr, <hi>Dr</hi> Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticar.</note> (which you have cited) to be noted<note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 3.</note> inſtead of many more, yet it doth not argue, but that the <hi>baptiſme</hi> holdeth firme, though in reſpect of the manner we allow it not, neither their additions thereunto; and though it be done by a <hi>wrong adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour</hi> upon an <hi>apoſtate,</hi> yet if that <hi>Apoſtate</hi> return from his <hi>apoſtaſie,</hi> the evill of the manner being repented of, the action hath no need to be done over again, neither doth <hi>God</hi> ſo require it, any more then he required the <hi>apoſtate Iſraelites</hi> (when they returned) to be <hi>circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed</hi> again; this you cannot deny, except you could prove <hi>baptiſme</hi> to be leſſe durable then <hi>circumciſion;</hi> as if <hi>Chriſt</hi> were leſſe faithfull in his houſe then <hi>Moſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again you ſay, <hi>the end for which Infants are baptiſed in the Church of England, is to regenerate them, and that they may be born anew, and accordingly it is concluded in the Catechiſme;</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 3.</note> 
               <hi>and confirmed by all theſe Authors, and divers others well known to your Miniſters, the maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of this doctrine, that in Baptiſme they receive the holy Spirit, that they are regenerate, and born anew; that they are made the members of Chriſt, the children of God, and heires of the kingdom of heaven. In an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to all which (you ſay) you ſhall ſay nothing, but onely reaſon this with ſome other of their own principles, and practiſe, and thereby</hi> (you ſay) <hi>you doubt not but it will appear to all, how unfaithfully they have, and do delude the Nations in this particular.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer. As for their unfaithfulneſſe, and their deluding the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, I doubt not of it; but with what do they moſt delude? if not
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:155922:7"/> with that which they have (like theeves) ſtolen away; So the <hi>whoriſh woman</hi> is ſaid to delude, by commending the ſtollen waters, and hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den bread for ſweetneſſe and pleaſantneſſe, (and ſo inticing her lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers to commit fornication with her<note n="a" place="margin">Pro. 9.1.7.</note>;) ſo the Philiſtines thought the Ark to be a rare thing<note n="b" place="margin">1 Sam. 4.7, 8, 9.</note>, and ſo indeed it was<note n="c" place="margin">Ver. 22.</note>, for it was Gods Arke, and not theirs, but ſacralegiouſly taken by them<note n="d" place="margin">Ver. 10.11. &amp;c.</note>, and put in their idolatrous high place for the honour of Dagan their God<note n="e" place="margin">Cap. 5. 1.2.</note>; yet it was not effectuall to ſave them from enemies, but rather to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them<note n="f" place="margin">Ver. 3.4, 5, 6, 7, 9.10.12.</note>: yet notwithſtanding after it was brought back again, the people of God enquired of God by it, and had an anſwer from him, which was effectuall for the delivering of all Iſrael <hi>whether they were Jews, or Proſolites of Paleſtina, or any other Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though the Iſraelites in their apoſtaſie deceived both them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and others, by retaining ſtill an outward profeſſion of God, and practiſing his outward ordinances, yea, and though they ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed unto devils, yet <hi>circumciſion</hi> was not worn out by them, nor repeated, when the <hi>Apoſtates</hi> returned, but remained true <hi>circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> both to <hi>young</hi> and <hi>old:</hi> and they, and their holy <hi>ſeed,</hi> were <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually,</hi> to have a part, and portion, in all the holy things of <hi>God,</hi> and alwayes as their <hi>children</hi> came to be capable, they were to mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt (actually) the fruits of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ods Spirit,</hi> both <hi>faith,</hi> and <hi>love,</hi> and all other graces: but if they afterward fell away, and ſo embraced the <hi>apoſtate</hi> condition (in which their fore-fathers formerly had been) though <hi>repentance</hi> and <hi>regeneration</hi> might be preached unto them, yet they had no part in <hi>Chriſts kingdome</hi> except they did repent, and become new creatures again; like the inceſtuous perſon in the Church of Corinth, when he was renewed again by <hi>repentance.</hi> And if any of the members in the viſible <hi>Church</hi> (though never ſo eminent) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſinne, they both may, and ought then to be admoniſhed to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance;</hi> Therefore it is no ſufficient argument to ſay, <hi>[that becauſe the Miniſters preach repentance, &amp;c. to them] that therefore the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme which they received is falſe. Simon Magus</hi> after he had beleeved, (and therefore was in all viſible account ſaved) was (upon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting of ſinne) admoniſhed by <hi>Peter</hi> to repentance; (yet his bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme was true) and ſo <hi>Judas Iſcariot</hi> though (he was) a <hi>Saint</hi> out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, yet afterward he appeared to be a <hi>devill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo farre as the <hi>Church of England both have, and will defend the doctrine of perſeverance in the regenerate, and members of Chriſt,</hi> they are in the right, though all the good deeds which they do (ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:155922:8"/> in point of juſtification, or ſanctification) ſhalt not avail them, in that eſtate; for the Lord abhorreth their beſt actions, as he did abhorre the beſt actions of the <hi>Apoſtate Iſraelites,</hi> and therefore <hi>cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion</hi> [as it was acted by them] was abhorred by him; but when any of them returned, he bound them not to be <hi>circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed</hi> again, but accepted of his own <hi>jewels</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">So Mr <hi>Spilsburie</hi> grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that the veſſels of the Lords houſe, they were Gods ordinances, &amp; that whiles they were in Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon, &amp;c. <hi>Dan.</hi> 5.2, 3. but not in reſpect of the uſe and ſervice the Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians applyed them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, &amp;c. Though in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſimply conſidered, they were Gods ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, ordained by him to a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſe, in which conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme may be ſaid to be Gods ordinance in the Church of Antichriſt. For this ſee his Treatiſe of Baptiſme, <hi>pa.</hi> 35. lin. 20. to lin. 27.</note>, though brought out of the ſinke and grave of Apoſtaſie.</p>
            <p>And ſo whatſoever <hi>good</hi> theſe Antichriſtians do is <hi>evill</hi> (as they do it) but if <hi>God</hi> give any of them a ſight of their ſinne, they are to repent of the <hi>evill</hi> of the <hi>manner:</hi> but for the <hi>good</hi> thing they have received, they ought not to throw it away, but own it as Gods.</p>
            <p>And ſurely a perſon may be eſteemed to be <hi>regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> and born again, though in Gods ſecret decree he was never <hi>elected.</hi> And yet theſe <hi>learned Divines</hi> (as you terme them) are not in ſuch a great ſtrait in defending this, though it be againſt the <hi>Arminians;</hi> for truth is more eaſie to be defended, then errour.</p>
            <p>Touching that <hi>all likelihood</hi> (which you bring, by entring into their heart) becauſe it is brought onely as a <hi>ſuppoſition,</hi> as it is ſleig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tly proved, ſo it deſerves to be ſleightly paſſed over. And your anſwer thereunto i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſomewhat like it,<note place="margin">Pag. 5.7.</note> being an anſwer to ſuch a likelihood, therefore it deſerves no reply: though in anſwer to theſe ſpeeches of yours (which you bring as ſuppoſitions or likelihoods) you adviſe the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors thereof <hi>to leave off ſuch jugling</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Pag 7. l. 16.</note>, <hi>and give glory to God in acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging the truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But after all this you make a ſimple objection on their behalfe, thus<note n="b" place="margin">Lin 21. 22.</note> 
               <hi>Infants are elected, and therefore they may be baptiſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which you anſwer<note n="c" place="margin">Lin. 23.24.</note>, that <hi>all Infants are not elected, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all infants ought not to be baptiſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I reply, that as the objection is without diſtinction, ſo is your anſwer thereunto; and therefore except they were explained, it were folly to anſwer either of them. For a man may be in Gods ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret election a <hi>Saint,</hi> and yet an <hi>Idolater,</hi> and ſo are the <hi>infants</hi> of ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous parents <hi>idolaters,</hi> (in regard of their viſible eſtate) yet we know not but that <hi>God</hi> hath elected divers of them, and will in his due time manifeſt them.</p>
            <p>But you make another weak objection for them: for you ſay, <hi>they
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:155922:8"/> will reply, That in regard ſome infants are elected, and none can ſay that this or that particular infant is not elected, therefore Baptiſme muſt be adminiſtred unto all, becauſe we may not deny the elect their priviledges, for fear of giving to others, that which belongs not to them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to this mad and fooliſh objection (which you father upon others) you make <hi>anſwer, that if it be a warrantable ground for you to adminiſter baptiſme to all infants, becauſe that ſome particular infants are elected, then by the ſame reaſon it will follow, that baptiſme may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully be adminiſtred to every man and woman in the world, becauſe amongſt them alſo we may judge that ſome are elected: But this</hi> (ſay you) <hi>contradicteth the order and rule of Chriſt.</hi> (Matth. 28.19. Mar. 16.16.) <hi>and muſt be ranked amongſt other of their ſophiſmes before detected</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">P. 8 l. 6. 7.</note>.</p>
            <p>To which I reply: That [ſome] <hi>infants</hi> are <hi>elected</hi> cannot be juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly denied; But to adminiſter <hi>baptiſme</hi> to [all] infants for fear of omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it to any of the <hi>elect,</hi> is to do evill that good may come thereof.</p>
            <p>Moreover, all the <hi>elect</hi> are not priviledged to have the outward or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of <hi>baptiſme,</hi> nor any of them till ſuch time as they are mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted unto us to be viſible <hi>Saints;</hi> Again, we know <hi>Judas Iſcariot,</hi> and <hi>Simon Magus</hi> were <hi>baptiſed,</hi> though not elected.</p>
            <p>Now the <hi>reaſon</hi> which is annexed to the <hi>objection,</hi> is nonſenſe, which is <hi>for fear of giving to others that which belongs not to them:</hi> for in adminiſtring <hi>Baptiſme</hi> to [all] they give unto others (beſides the <hi>elect</hi>) that which belongeth not to them; therefore ſuch <hi>manner</hi> of reaſoning will not ſtand; I ſeldome have heard the like reaſoning, except it were amongſt thoſe who deny <hi>Infants baptiſme</hi> to be Gods holy inſtitution.</p>
            <p>Now in your anſwer to this you croſſe your ſelf; in <hi>pag.</hi> 7. lin. 9, 10, 11. where you ſay, that God hath not ſaid he will deſtroy any <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants</hi> in hell, and it would be cenſorious for any to judge that they ſhall be damned, and yet you grant concerning perſons of yeers that they are under the cenſure of damnation. Therefore by your own ground you cannot ſo freely <hi>baptiſe</hi> all men and women as you can all infants, and therefore it appears that what you build up with one hand, you throw down with the other.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond part of your anſwer to this <hi>objection,</hi> you grant <hi>(for arguments ſake) that baptiſme is to be adminiſtred upon the elect before they manifeſt faith,</hi> in which affirmation, you want a diſtinction, and explanation, for you ought to have made a diſtinction betweene <hi>faith inherent,</hi> and <hi>faith profeſſed;</hi> that is, you ſhould have declared
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:155922:9"/> that faith may be <hi>inherent</hi> in ſome onely; and <hi>profeſſed</hi> in others.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that all that <hi>profeſſe faith verbally</hi> have not faith <hi>really;</hi> and all that have <hi>faith really,</hi> do not <hi>profeſſe</hi> it <hi>verbally,</hi> or manifeſt it themſelves <hi>actually.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, you ſhould have explained your ſelf, whether you meane by the <hi>elect,</hi> all the <hi>elect,</hi> or but <hi>ſome</hi> of them, all which you have omitted: wherefore I <hi>omit to anſwer you till you further explain your ſelf.</hi> But in the concluſion you affirm, <hi>that its true faith onely mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted, and made known by confeſſion of the mouth, that gives the elect ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to Baptiſme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, that though we cannot know <hi>inviſibly</hi> becauſe it is the onely office of the <hi>inviſible Spirit,</hi> to whom all things are <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible,</hi> yet we may <hi>judge</hi> of <hi>inviſible things,</hi> by <hi>viſible demonſtrations;</hi> as the <hi>Saints</hi> before us have done; ſo <hi>God</hi> leaving unto us a <hi>rule</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to judge the <hi>infants</hi> of <hi>beleevers</hi> to be <hi>elected,</hi> it is want of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and charitie which maketh ſome perſons that they cannot judge ſo of them, nor put a difference between the <hi>infants</hi> of <hi>heathens</hi> and the <hi>infants</hi> of <hi>beleeving parents;</hi> for the <hi>infants</hi> of <hi>beleevers</hi> in the time of the <hi>Law</hi> could not be <hi>circumciſed</hi> (according to <hi>Gods</hi> will) without a <hi>confeſſion;</hi> but if their <hi>parents</hi> made a <hi>confeſſion,</hi> it was ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to bring both them and their <hi>infants</hi> to have right to <hi>circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion,</hi> and thoſe <hi>infants</hi> were <hi>Jews</hi> (that is, <hi>confeſſors</hi>) though they could not make a <hi>verball confeſſion</hi> themſelves <hi>actually</hi> and the like priviledge the <hi>infants</hi> of <hi>beleevers</hi> have now under the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> to have <hi>baptiſme,</hi> as the other had <hi>circumciſion,</hi> which is one and the ſame in effect. But when any of the <hi>Jews</hi> apoſtated, they loſt the name; and ſo theſe <hi>idolaters</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>England</hi> are as thoſe <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates</hi> then were, and ſo is their <hi>off-ſpring.</hi> And when we call the <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleeving Hebrews</hi> by the name of <hi>Jews</hi> (or Iſraelites,) it is but onely for diſtinction ſake: for as the dumbe Idols were called <hi>Gods,</hi> and yet were no <hi>gods,</hi> ſo thoſe are no <hi>Jews</hi> which <hi>confeſſe</hi> not <hi>Chriſt</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 9.6. and 2.28.</note>; but if any do imbrace <hi>Christ</hi> in puritie, both they and their <hi>infants</hi> have right to <hi>baptiſme,</hi> (as really,) as the <hi>infants</hi> of the beleeving <hi>Jews</hi> had right to <hi>circumciſion</hi> they being in the <hi>covenant.</hi> Elſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhould be leſſe faithfull in his houſe then <hi>Moſes.</hi> For <hi>infants</hi> were by God counted worthy of the <hi>ſigne</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 17.11.</note> and <hi>ſeal</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 4.11.</note> of his <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> both before<note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 17.7.9, 10, 11.14. Exod. 12.48.</note> and under the <hi>Law</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Joſ. 5.7. Luk. 1.59.</note>; and <hi>Chriſt</hi> coming into the <hi>world,</hi> came not to take away any priviledge from any <hi>infant</hi> which former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enjoyed the ſame, but placed as great a one (if not greater) in the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:155922:9"/> ſtead thereof, he came not to take away the <hi>types</hi> from the <hi>infants</hi> of <hi>beleevers,</hi> and bereave them both of <hi>ſubſtances</hi> and <hi>types,</hi> but ſeeing <hi>baptiſme</hi> is come in ſtead of <hi>circumciſion,</hi> as the <hi>infants</hi> of <hi>beleevers</hi> formerly had right to <hi>circumciſion,</hi> ſo the <hi>infants</hi> of <hi>beleevers</hi> now have right to <hi>baptiſme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus, though you have paſſed from your <hi>firſt</hi> particular, to your <hi>fifth,</hi> from the <hi>end,</hi> to the <hi>ſubject,</hi> yet I have given you a direct <hi>anſwer unto both.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>THe ſecond particular,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 9.</note> which you bring (for diſproof of the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme in the Church of England (is, <hi>the manner in which baptiſme is there adminiſtred, which manner</hi> (you ſay) <hi>is ſprinkling, or caſting a little water upon the head or face of the child baptiſed, wherein</hi> (you ſay) <hi>they ſhew themſelves as contrary to Chriſt as in the former particular. Foraſmuch as the inſtitution of Chriſt requireth that the whole man be dipped all over in water.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſwer, that there is little weight in this confuſed ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of yours, as may plainly appear in obſerving the particulars; for you lay it down ambiguouſly, in ſaying the <hi>[head] or face of the child;</hi> If you meane that becauſe the <hi>face</hi> is a part of the <hi>head,</hi> that they in <hi>baptiſing</hi> the <hi>face, baptiſe</hi> the <hi>head,</hi> in it I aſſent unto you; but if by the <hi>head</hi> you meane the <hi>ſcull,</hi> (or hairy place of the head) if you ſay they <hi>baptiſe</hi> that part by <hi>ſprinkling</hi> or <hi>caſting</hi> water thereon, I doubt not but you are miſtaken.</p>
            <p>But you would have the whole man to be <hi>dipt all over in water,</hi> and this <hi>inſtitution</hi> you would father upon <hi>Chriſt;</hi> But in this your own bare affirmation (though not yours onely) the Scripture will not beare you out.</p>
            <p>But for confirmation of this your opinion of dipping every part, you quote divers Scriptures, as <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.11. <hi>Mark</hi> 1.8. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.26. <hi>Act.</hi> 11.16. and you tell us they <hi>point out a baptiſme</hi> [in] <hi>water, but not a baptiſme</hi> [with] <hi>water</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Lin. 21.</note>.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, that if they point not out <hi>baptiſme</hi> [with] <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> then they point out a <hi>baptiſme</hi> [without] <hi>water,</hi> but I thought you had intended to ſpeak here onely of the <hi>baptiſme</hi> of <hi>water</hi> (for ſo the Scriptures quoted do) and if that be your meaning, I pray you to ſhew (if you can) how theſe Scriptures (or any other) do point out ſuch a baptiſme [in] water, and yet not [with] water: To ſay it is the <hi>baptiſme</hi> of water, and yet not [with] water, argueth an impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibilitie, and is (in the ſelf ſame reſpect) a flat contradiction, yea, and contrary to reaſon.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:155922:10"/>
            <p>Indeed if you had not repeated it again<note n="a" place="margin">Lin. 24.</note>, and <hi>that in the ſame terms without alteration,</hi> I might have thought it had been onely an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight of yours. But finding the ſame thing inſiſted upon again<note n="b" place="margin">Lin. 27. 29.</note> and again<note n="c" place="margin">Pa. 10. lin 8.</note>, charitie it ſelf would not permit me to judge otherwiſe, but that your words ſeem to import, that perſons may receive the true <hi>baptiſme</hi> of <hi>water</hi> [in] <hi>water;</hi> and yet not [with] <hi>water.</hi> For (after you have quoted <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.11. <hi>Ego men baptizo humas en hudati, I indeed baptize you in water, Mar.</hi> 1.8. <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>baptiſa humas en hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dati, I indeed have baptiſed you in water.</hi> Alſo <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.26. <hi>Act.</hi> 11.16.) you ſay, <hi>all theſe point out a baptiſme [in] water, but not a baptiſme [with] water.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas<note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 9. li. 22.23.</note> the word [en] (in <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.21. <hi>Kai hoi loipoi apoct atheſanente romthaia</hi>) ſignifieth with.</p>
            <p>You anſwer, that <hi>it never ſignifieth with, after this word baptizo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another reaſon you alledge from Chriſts being <hi>baptiſed</hi> into the Jordan.<note place="margin">Pag. 9. Pag. 10.</note> Therefore you conclude again that <hi>this word</hi> [en] (<hi>as uſed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this word</hi> baptizo) <hi>muſt ſignifie [in] and not [with.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But you ſhould take notice that if <hi>Chriſt</hi> received the <hi>baptiſme</hi> of <hi>water,</hi> he was <hi>baptiſed</hi> not onely when he was in <hi>Jordan,</hi> but there was he <hi>baptiſed</hi> [with] the <hi>water</hi> of <hi>Jordan.</hi> Wherefore it plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth that the word [en] in this place ſignifieth [with] and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you have not done well to ſay it doth not. You alledge <hi>Greeke</hi> and <hi>Latine</hi>) Authors to prove that the word <hi>en (as uſed after this word baptizo)</hi> muſt ſignifie <hi>in</hi> and not <hi>with.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which thing is contrary to the Scriptures which ſpeake of the <hi>baptiſme</hi> of <hi>water,</hi> neither can ſuch an affirmation ſtand with reaſon, but is contradictory to it ſelf, and therefore not to be beleeved.</p>
            <p>But the dipping of the whole man all over in water is that you ſtand for; but yet you have not proved it to be of Chriſts ordaining, you deny both <hi>waſhing</hi> and <hi>ſprinkling</hi> with <hi>water,</hi> to be <hi>Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance;</hi> and affirme dipping is the onely right way: but ſeeing you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie the former, how will you take (or how have you taken) up the latter: if you hold it ſucceſſively, to the ſucceſſours you muſt then go, if you have not found (or cannot find) them which way then have you taken (or which way wil you take) it up? But by one whom you judge to be an unbaptiſed perſon. Moreover, you tell us that <hi>the whole man muſt be dipped all over,</hi> but you declare not unto us the way and manner thereof; whether the ſubject muſt go into the <hi>water</hi> himſelf, or whether he muſt be put in by another, or onely led in, or
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:155922:10"/> carried; or (if the party muſt go in) whether he muſt be lifted up, out of the <hi>water,</hi> and ſo dipped <hi>down</hi> again, or no; or whether, onely that part that is <hi>above</hi> the <hi>water,</hi> (muſt be dipt, and that <hi>part under</hi> the <hi>water</hi> let alone) or if the <hi>ſubject</hi> be <hi>dipped</hi> all but a <hi>part,</hi> whether he muſt be <hi>dipped again</hi> in <hi>whole,</hi> or in <hi>part,</hi> or if there be any <hi>errour</hi> in your <hi>dipping,</hi> in <hi>omiſſion</hi> or <hi>commiſſion</hi> whether it maketh a nullitie of your <hi>ordinance,</hi> how your judgement ſtandeth in theſe things I know not: you ſtand for <hi>dipping,</hi> yea and <hi>dipping the whole man all over in water;</hi> not onely the <hi>feet,</hi> but alſo the <hi>hands</hi> and <hi>head;</hi> but what if ſome part or parts be miſſing? is it not true baptiſme? But further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more how ſhall this baptiſme be done by a weak perſon, eſpecially in great and deep waters (which thing you urge in your diſcourſe) how ſhall this dipping of every part be done in ſuch rivers where the ſtreame is readie to carrie them away (eſpecially when he who is the baptiſer is weak of body, and lifteth up the (man or woman) above the water) theſe things are to be obſerved alſo.</p>
            <p>But ſurely it is not good to preſume above what is written in the Word of God, either in juſtifying of our ſelves, or condemning of others. And if you do but well obſerve the manner how <hi>Philip</hi> bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed the <hi>Eunuch,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 8.36.38.</note> peradventure you may receive ſome light in this point, whereby you may be diſſwaded from your totall <hi>dipping:</hi> for it is ſaid that <hi>Philip</hi> and the <hi>Eunuch</hi> went both down into the <hi>water,</hi> and there <hi>Philip</hi> baptiſed the <hi>Eunuch,</hi> which doth plainly demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, unto us, that going into the <hi>water</hi> is no part of <hi>baptiſme;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>baptiſme</hi> was adminiſtred after their going into the <hi>water;</hi> for if it had been a part of <hi>baptiſme,</hi> then the <hi>Eunuch</hi> baptiſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, for he went into the water. But the Scripture ſaith, that <hi>they went down both into the water, both Philip and the Eunuch, and he bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him.</hi> Neither is it ſaid, that <hi>Philip baptiſed himſelf</hi> (which by the ſame reaſon we may conceive he did, if <hi>going</hi> into the <hi>water</hi> were a part of <hi>baptiſme</hi>) but the Scripture noteth the going down into the <hi>water,</hi> and the being <hi>baptiſed</hi> with the <hi>water,</hi> as two diſtinct things. Neither is it ſaid, that <hi>Philip baptiſed</hi> the <hi>Eunuchs feet,</hi> or <hi>legs,</hi> for the <hi>Eunuch</hi> was in the <hi>water</hi> before, and at the time of his <hi>baptiſme,</hi> but it is ſaid, <hi>Philip baptiſed</hi> him; to wit, a part of <hi>him</hi> for the whole, which part in reaſon muſt be conceived to be his <hi>face,</hi> under which externall noble part is comprehended the whole man, and all the ſenſes of his body. So the Scriptures in divers places teacheth us to underſtand, that a <hi>part</hi> ſometimes is to be taken for the <hi>whole;</hi> ſo it
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:155922:11"/> was propheſied, that the Son of man ſhould be three dayes and three nights in the heart of the earth<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 12.40.</note>, and yet he lay not there ſo long, but roſe before three dayes or three nights was totally expired; as appeareth by <hi>Matth.</hi> 27.46. and 28.1 6 7. <hi>Mar.</hi> 15.42. and 16.2.9. <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.54 56. and 24.1 36. <hi>Joh.</hi> 19.42. and 20.1.14.19. All which doth teach us in ſome caſes of great concernment (as this was about <hi>Chriſts</hi>) to underſtand that ſometimes when the <hi>whole</hi> is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, but a <hi>part</hi> is meant: For to confirm this, you may ſee here, that we have the words and teſtimonies of <hi>Angels, Apoſtles, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> and <hi>Saints,</hi> yea and of <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf: If then in ſome things of the greateſt concernment we may and muſt take a <hi>part</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Luk. 24. Mat. 17.23.</note> for the <hi>whole</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 12.40.</note>, ſure then in ſome things [of leſſer moment] we may, and muſt take a part for the whole. For it is not to be thought that <hi>God</hi> hath tyed to baptiſe every member of our body, (which ſhall be raiſed at the day of judgement) that the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> ſo did <hi>baptiſe;</hi> neither can you prove, that the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> did ſo <hi>baptiſe,</hi> except you meane that a part is to be taken for the whole, as I have ſhewed before. And ſeeing that <hi>Act.</hi> 8.38, 39 (concerning <hi>Philips baptiſing</hi> the <hi>Eunuch</hi>) is brought by you<note n="c" place="margin">See his book, pa. 11. lin. 1.</note> to prove (as I ſuppoſe) that <hi>Philip baptiſed</hi> every externall part of his body, and that by way of dipping) prove the thing, I ſay, (if you can) and then you will ſpeak to ſome purpoſe in maintenance of your totall dipping. If you cannot do it, to what end then have you brought this Scripture which maketh againſt you?</p>
            <p>Conſider, I pray you, that <hi>Paul</hi> after the Lord had ſmitten him down<note n="d" place="margin">Act. 9.4.</note>, was without his ſight, but was led unto Damaſcus to the houſe of <hi>Judas,</hi> and there remained, in a weak condition, (not having his ſight) nor taking any food for the ſpace of three dayes<note n="e" place="margin">Ver 8 9.11.</note>, his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die being ſo enfeebled<note n="f" place="margin">Ver. 18.19.</note> ſhall we think that it would not have been an act of crueltie (Egyptian like) to have dipped him over head and eares in cold water? which thing I ſuppoſe you hold. For you cry out for <hi>dipping the whole man all over in water,</hi> and why will not the ſame rule which you have for <hi>dipping</hi> every part ſerve for <hi>waſhing,</hi> or <hi>ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> the ſame parts?</p>
            <p>O but (ſay you) Baptiſme in the Church of <hi>England</hi> is not <hi>Gods ordinance,</hi> becauſe it is adminiſtred by ſprinkling, or <hi>caſting water up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſubject:</hi> &amp; you except againſt infuſing or powring the water up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (and therewith waſhing) the ſubject<note n="*" place="margin">See <hi>A.R.</hi> p. 9 li 16. p. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. l. 3.</note> But if you did but conſider and read the Scriptures with underſtanding, and good judgement, you might perceive this manner to be right according to the rules
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:155922:11"/> and coherences of Scripture; for ſprinkling (or putting water upon perſons in <hi>baptiſme</hi>) hath been not onely an ancient cuſtome, but an act of Gods own acting and ordaining. God opened the windows of heaven, and powred down water in the time of <hi>Noah,</hi> and this was his manner of baptiſing then.</p>
            <p>And God himſelf baptiſed the children of Iſrael in the Red ſea, not by overwhelming them with water, as he did the Egyptians, but by ſprinkling or infuſing water upon them<note n="g" place="margin">Pſal 16.17.19.20.</note>; and yet <hi>Paul</hi> gives it the denomination of <hi>baptiſme</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">1 Cor. 10.1.2.</note>, and therefore though baptiſme be adminiſtred by ſprinkling it is the very right baptiſme.</p>
            <p>And ſurely you have not well conſidered (or at leaſt not explained your ſelf) in ſaying, that <hi>the waſhing of cups is not a putting or infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing water upon the cups</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">See <hi>A. R.</hi> p. 10. li. 21. 22.23.</note>; If you meane that it cannot be done by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing water upon them, I affirm and will prove that it may be done by waſhing without dipping: whether they be cups or platters. But you ſhould have conſidered that perſons waſh their faces by putting water thereon, this common experience teacheth us: ſo the Prophet <hi>Eliah</hi> waſhed his hands by <hi>water powred</hi> upon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2 King. 3.11.</note>, done by his own ſervant <hi>Eliſha;</hi> and in reaſon a man may with more eaſe &amp; leſſe trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble dip his hands, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his face: yet you may ſee the <hi>Prophet</hi> made clean his hands by having water <hi>powred</hi> upon them. And therfore (if reaſon it ſelf would not teach us) the Scripture would, that cups may be waſh d by powring water upon them, and made as clean, yea cleaner then if they were dipt without cleanſing or waſhing: but by this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection of yours you would intimate that ſo farre as you <hi>dip</hi> ſo farre you <hi>waſh:</hi> or elſe of what weight is your ſpeech of waſhing cups by putting them in water after your manner of dipping.</p>
            <p>Again, we may conſider that ſprinkling was appointed of God in the time of the Law; the aſhes of the Red heifer mixed with living water<note n="*" place="margin">Numb. 19.</note> was for this uſe, of ſprinkling the people.</p>
            <p>And I ſuppoſe you cannot deny but ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> baptiſme anſwereth that, as well as the baptiſme of <hi>Noah</hi> in the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k or Iſrael in the Sea. And I doubt not but that the <hi>baptiſme</hi> of <hi>Noah</hi> was a reſemblance of our <hi>buriall</hi> with <hi>Chriſt:</hi> neither dare I affirme otherwiſe, but that the <hi>baptiſme</hi> that now is, is a <hi>like figure</hi> anſwerable to that; but <hi>Peter</hi> telleth us it is <hi>not the waſhing away <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f the filth of the fleſh,</hi> but it is a <hi>bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme</hi> which <hi>ſaveth us by the reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> 1 Pet. 3 20, 21 And <hi>ſprinkling</hi> and waſhing hath a ſimilitude with the <hi>death, bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall,</hi> and the <hi>reſurrection</hi> of Chriſt: for thoſe that are ſprinkled and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:155922:12"/> waſhed with the blood of Chriſt, are dead unto ſinne, and do live unto righteouſneſſe. <hi>The Law was their Schoolmaſter to lead them unto Chriſt;</hi> but <hi>ſprinkling</hi> was a part of the <hi>Law,</hi> an action of <hi>Gods</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, therefore it was to lead them unto <hi>Chriſt:</hi> and if we do but obſerve, we ſhall underſtand that the <hi>Red heifer</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Num. 19</note> was a <hi>figure</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the killing of it, and burning it on the <hi>Altar,</hi> ſignified the <hi>death</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and his <hi>bitter</hi> paſſion; the <hi>Aſhes</hi> being to be mixed with living water, and ſo that water to ſprinkle the people ſet all this forth unto them: It was to teach them that the blood of <hi>Chriſt</hi> was onely ſufficient to purge ſinne, it was therefore to teach them <hi>morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication</hi> of the old man, a <hi>dying</hi> to ſinne, and a <hi>living</hi> to righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, through the mercie of <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>Meſſias</hi> who was then to come; yea, and it did alſo really figure out unto them, <hi>Gods</hi> graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>acceptation</hi> of them, and of that <hi>ſacrifice</hi> for them, for ſo the turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>burnt offering</hi> unto <hi>aſhes</hi> did <hi>ſignifie</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 20.3.</note>, and ſo the ſprinkling was to put them in mind of the ſame; and whereas it was mixed with <hi>living water,</hi> and ſo impoſed upon them, it was to teach them, that ſo their <hi>ſinnes</hi> ſhould be waſhed away through <hi>Chriſt:</hi> and to this the Apoſtle alludeth, where he mentioneth <hi>pure water.</hi> Now he that is a <hi>ſelf-denying Chriſtian, dead</hi> unto ſin, and ſo mortified, he is <hi>buried with Chriſt by a baptiſme without hands;</hi> And when he apprehends <hi>Gods</hi> gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious love and mercy, and free acceptation of him through Chriſt, he may wel be ſaid to be riſen with <hi>Chriſt:</hi> all theſe things the ſprinkling was to teach them, to behold <hi>Chriſts day afarre off;</hi> And yet you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to ſay, that <hi>ſprinkling or waſhing without dipping hath no [ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude] with death, burying, and riſing again</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Treat. <hi>A.R</hi> p. 11. li. 24.25.</note>: But why then doth the Scripture ſo plentifully ſet forth our mortification, repentance from dead works, dying to ſin, and living to righteouſnes under ſuch terms<note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 10.22.23. &amp; 12.24. Eze. 36.25</note> as <hi>waſhing</hi> and <hi>ſprinkling,</hi> if <hi>ſprinkling</hi> and <hi>waſhing</hi> did not bear out a <hi>ſimilitude</hi> thereof. And why doth the Scripture give that the deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of <hi>baptiſme</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 10.1.2. Luk. 12.50. Iſa. 52.14.</note>, which was not done by <hi>dipping</hi> them (or plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging them) in the element. Surely theſe things being rightly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, it will evidently appear, that the <hi>baptiſme</hi> done by <hi>ſprinkling</hi> and <hi>waſhing</hi> is not onely a full reſemblance of our <hi>mortification</hi> or <hi>waſhing</hi> from our <hi>ſinnes,</hi> and the <hi>cleanſing</hi> of our ſouls by <hi>Chriſts blood,</hi> and ſo a <hi>dying</hi> to ſinne, and a <hi>living</hi> to righteouſneſſe<note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. 6.11.</note>; a put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on of <hi>Chriſt</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Gal. 3.27.</note>, &amp;c. but alſo holds forth unto us the death of <hi>[Chriſt]</hi> and his <hi>bitter</hi> paſſion<note n="c" place="margin">Luk. 12.50.</note>, yea <hi>ſelf-denyall,</hi> and forſaking of all for <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſake, as much, yea, and much more then <hi>dipping</hi> the <hi>whole man</hi> without <hi>waſhing</hi> can do.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:155922:12"/>
            <p>Yea the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> intimateth that the <hi>externall baptiſme</hi> is a <hi>waſhing</hi> away of the filth of the <hi>fleſh</hi> (holding forth no more then an <hi>externall ordinance</hi> can hold forth. This <hi>Peter</hi> could ſpeak by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, for he knew that <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> who beleeved outwardly had the outward <hi>waſhing,</hi> and yet manifeſted himſelf afterwards to be <hi>in the gall of bitterneſſe, and in the bonds of iniquitie</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Act 8.23</note>;) but the <hi>bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme</hi> which is onely available to ſalvation, is <hi>the anſwer of a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> toward God, that is the <hi>baptiſme</hi> indeed <hi>which ſaveth by the reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">1 Pet. 3 21.</note>: Now he that hath his heart <hi>ſprinkled</hi> with the <hi>blood</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> he may fully aſſure himſelf that he ſhall be <hi>ſaved,</hi> and ſo he is <hi>riſen</hi> with <hi>Chriſt</hi> though he want the <hi>outward bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme</hi> (which you grant is <hi>nothing in compariſon of Chriſt</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">In the ſecond Treatiſe, pa. 17.</note>) and ſo he having part in <hi>Chriſt</hi> who is <hi>the reſurrection and the life</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Joh. 11.25.</note>, <hi>he ſhall not be hurt with the ſecond death.</hi> Rev. 2.11. and 20.6.</p>
            <p>But this your <hi>dipping of the whole man all over in water,</hi> you would have to hold forth not onely <hi>death</hi> and <hi>buriall,</hi> but alſo a <hi>riſing again:</hi> and for this end you mention ſome words of the <hi>Apoſtle Paul, Col.</hi> 2.12. <hi>Buried with him by baptiſme, wherein you are alſo riſen with him, &amp;c.</hi> Rom. 6.4.5. <hi>We are buried with him by baptiſme into his death. And if we have been planted together in the likeneſſe of his death, we ſhall alſo in the likeneſſe of his reſurrection. And in</hi> 1. Cor. 15.29. <hi>St. Paul amongſt other arguments to prove the reſurrection hath theſe words, What ſhall they do which are baptiſed for dead, if the dead riſe not at all; why then are they baptiſed for dead?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> The firſt Scripture (<hi>Col.</hi> 2.12.) ſpeaketh of a <hi>reſurrection</hi> then preſent, and the other Scriptures (<hi>Rom.</hi> 6.5. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.29.) ſpeake of a <hi>reſurrection</hi> to come. Now in the reſurrection at the <hi>day</hi> of <hi>judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> the <hi>blind</hi> ſhall receive their ſight<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 1.7 Job 19.24, 25, 26.27.</note>, though the <hi>eyes</hi> which are the inſtrument of their ſight are periſhed; and though a perſon have loſt his <hi>legs,</hi> or his <hi>armes,</hi> or any <hi>externall member</hi> of his body, (that is not ſuperfluous) yet he being not thereby killed is (according to his capabilitie) ſtill to <hi>beleeve,</hi> that all thoſe breaches ſhall be made up in the <hi>reſurrection:</hi> now if you ſhould happen to <hi>baptiſe</hi> ſuch a one by <hi>dipping</hi> which hath ſuch defects in nature, as the want of his <hi>legs, armes,</hi> or <hi>eyes,</hi> &amp;c. will you ſay that that <hi>baptiſme</hi> ſetteth forth unto him no more but onely the <hi>raiſing</hi> of thoſe <hi>externall parts</hi> which you then <hi>dip;</hi> then you will have it to ſet forth a <hi>blind</hi> (or <hi>lame) reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</hi> But if you will ſay, the baptiſme he receiveth at your hands ſetteth forth the <hi>reſurrection</hi> of all the <hi>parts,</hi> both thoſe parts that are
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:155922:13"/> miſſing, and thoſe parts that are not; thoſe members that are <hi>baptiſed</hi> and thoſe members that are not <hi>baptiſed:</hi> then the caſe is evident that (the eminents <hi>part</hi> (or parts) of the <hi>body</hi> being <hi>baptiſed</hi>) the ſaid <hi>baptiſme</hi> ſetteth forth the ſame benefit unto the reſt of the members; for in the <hi>reſurrection</hi> if one member be had in honour, all ſhall be had in honour.</p>
            <p>For further explaining of the matter, I put this ordinarie caſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, (and deſire you to conſider thereof) Suppoſe a man come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you to be <hi>baptiſed,</hi> and wanteth one, or both of his <hi>legs, arms, eyes,</hi> or other <hi>externall members,</hi> what now is to be done in this caſe? Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure you will ſay that you <hi>cannot baptiſe thoſe members that are not to be found;</hi> So ſay I too: But what then? if thoſe members were (or are) to be found? muſt you needs ſeek for thoſe; to baptiſe them with him? You will ſay, <hi>No! that would be a ſenſleſſe thing to baptiſe that which hath no more life in it then a ſtone!</hi> I alſo affirm the ſame. But what is further to be done? will you proceed and baptiſe this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leever, or leave him unbaptiſed? You will ſay, <hi>He is a beleever, though he want his eyes, legges, armes, &amp;c. and therefore he muſt be baptiſed, though he want thoſe externall members.</hi> Yea, but then I ask you whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you do not conceive that your <hi>baptiſme</hi> is a <hi>buriall,</hi> and a <hi>riſing again,</hi> and whether you do not beleeve that it ſetteth forth unto the lame man the <hi>reſurrection</hi> of [all] his members, as well as if all his members had been <hi>baptiſed;</hi> I ſuppoſe you will ſay, <hi>Why not? there is no reaſon can be given to the contrarie, conſidering that thoſe members ſhall be raiſed with the body at the reſurrection.</hi> But then I deſire you to remember this, and beare in mind what will follow, namely, that <hi>baptiſme</hi> ſetteth forth the <hi>reſurrection</hi> of thoſe externall members which were never <hi>baptiſed,</hi> and therefore that which you eſteeme to be no <hi>baptiſme,</hi> or but a <hi>baptiſing</hi> [in part] ſetteth forth the <hi>reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> of the [whole] bodie; and ſo totally of [all] the members there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and belonging thereunto; ſo that the face (or eminents part of a man) being <hi>baptiſed</hi> though the reſt of the members are not wet with water, yet this <hi>baptiſme</hi> holdeth forth the <hi>reſurrection</hi> of the whole body. I meane not onely a ſpirituall <hi>reſurrection,</hi> but a <hi>tranſlation</hi> of the <hi>naturall</hi> body into a <hi>ſpirituall</hi> body, and this is the <hi>reſurrection</hi> the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſpeaketh of when he ſaith, <hi>What ſhall they do that are bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed for the dead, if the dead riſe not at all? why then are they baptiſed for dead?</hi> 1. Cor. 15 9.</p>
            <p>Your concluſion of this point<note n="*" place="margin">Pa. 12.</note> which is grounded upon a ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:155922:13"/> I reject, becauſe it openly contradicteth the Scripture, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.2.1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.27. <hi>Matth.</hi> 20.22. <hi>Luke</hi> 12.50. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.15. For you ſay, that <hi>he that is not dipped, is not baptiſed;</hi> and that <hi>all thoſe that have the adminiſtration of baptiſme by ſprinkling, or by any waſhing without dipping are unbaptiſed.</hi> Which I denie, and that from the grounds before alledged; remember (I pray you) how you urge the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the quantitie of the <hi>element,</hi> to be of ſuch neceſſitie to <hi>bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme,</hi> that except a perſon have ſo much, wherein he may <hi>dip</hi> the whole man all over, <hi>baptiſme</hi> cannot be rightly adminiſtred upon him; and ſo by your grounds not adminiſtred at all.</p>
            <p>And this is one of the particulars, by which you would diſprove the <hi>baptiſme</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, though in the <hi>Church of England</hi> the <hi>manner</hi> of <hi>baptiſing</hi> is by <hi>ſprinkling, waſhing,</hi> or <hi>powring</hi> the water upon the moſt eminent part of the ſubject, which is there preſented to be <hi>baptiſed,</hi> yet in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and in ſome places of <hi>England,</hi> and the dominions of <hi>Wales,</hi> they have uſed, and do uſe <hi>dipping</hi> of perſons in the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of <hi>baptiſme;</hi> which is a thing [in reſpect of the <hi>manner</hi>] plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing unto you (and therefore in this <hi>ſecond particular</hi> not here ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted againſt by you) for in ſtriking at the <hi>manner,</hi> you have in this touched nothing, but [onely] their <hi>waſhing, ſprinkling,</hi> or <hi>powring</hi> of <hi>water</hi> upon the partie, whereon it is adminiſtred.</p>
            <p>Your <hi>third ground</hi> (or <hi>particular</hi>) by which you labour<note n="*" place="margin">Pa. 12. at lin. 26.</note> to diſprove the <hi>baptiſme</hi> in the <hi>Church of England,</hi> and make it to be of none effect, is, <hi>becauſe of the Antichriſtian power, authoritie, and office of mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery by which it is adminiſtred:</hi> and ſo you conclude, that becauſe their power and authority is not of Chriſt: therefore the baptiſme is not from Chriſt<note n="*" place="margin">Pa. 13. lin. 1.2.</note>.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, That I grant they have no enrighting <hi>power</hi> to adminiſter any of the holy things of <hi>God,</hi> no more then the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate Iſraelites,</hi> yet as that <hi>Antichriſtian power</hi> by which they did ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter, deſtroyed not <hi>circumciſion,</hi> but that it remained true <hi>cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion:</hi> ſo <hi>baptiſme,</hi> (being as dureable as <hi>circumciſion</hi>) it cannot be worne out by theſe <hi>Apoſtates,</hi> no more then <hi>circumciſion</hi> was by the other.</p>
            <p>And what <hi>right</hi> had the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> to the <hi>Arke?</hi> or what <hi>authority</hi> had the <hi>Babylonians</hi> to ſteal the <hi>veſſels</hi> of the <hi>Lord?</hi> or what <hi>power</hi> had <hi>Idolaters</hi> to lay ſacralegious hands upon any of his <hi>holy inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions?</hi> Surely they had no ſuch commiſſion, either from <hi>God</hi> or
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:155922:14"/> 
               <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſo to do; yet, I hope, you will not ſay, that the <hi>Arke</hi> was no <hi>Arke,</hi> the <hi>veſſels</hi> no <hi>veſſels,</hi> the <hi>inſtitutions</hi> (as in themſelves) <hi>nothing</hi> at all; for then you would <hi>openly</hi> contradict the Scripture<note n="*" place="margin">1. Sam. 4. &amp; 5. Dan 5.3.23. Ezra 6.5. Ezek. 43.8. Rev. 11.2.</note>. The like may be ſaid concerning <hi>Gods inſtitutions</hi> under the defection of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt,</hi> the <hi>marriage,</hi> is <hi>marriage;</hi> though the manner be not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed <hi>lawfully:</hi> the <hi>Word</hi> is the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>baptiſme</hi> his own, though in <hi>apoſtaſie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay<note n="*" place="margin">Pa. 13. at li. 25</note>, that as the <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt hath no where in his Word ordained or appointed any women to adminiſter his baptiſme. Nor no more hath he any where in his Word authoriſed any men by any falſe power to adminiſter his baptiſme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer. The like may be ſaid concerning <hi>circumciſion;</hi> We read not that any woman had authoritie (from God) to <hi>circumciſe</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">And yet Mr <hi>Spilsbery</hi> in his Treat ſe of Bap p. 33. lin. 47.48. ſaith, he ſeeth not but that in caſe of nec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſity a woman might lawfully cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſe, ſhe being no where prohibited. But by the ſame rule of his, a woman may lawfully baptiſe.</note>: yet the act being done by <hi>Ziporah</hi> [a woman] it was not falſe <hi>cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion;</hi> and <hi>God</hi> (who is <hi>the God of order</hi>) never gave wicked men any order to <hi>circumciſe,</hi> or any one by any <hi>falſe power</hi> to adminiſter his <hi>ſigne,</hi> and <hi>ſeale</hi> of the <hi>righteouſneſſe of faith;</hi> and yet though it were adminiſtred in that <hi>Apoſtate eſtate,</hi> of Iſrael by apoſtates, and upon Apoſtates, yet it made no anullitie of the ordinance, but was the <hi>ſigne</hi> and <hi>ſeale</hi> of the righteouſneſſe of faith to thoſe that returned out of the grave of that <hi>Apoſtaſie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore the ground which you draw by ſimilitude from the <hi>civill</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ates (applying the ſame comparatively to the <hi>ſpirituall</hi>) will not ſerve your turne. For the Kings Proclamations are his, though proclaimed by any: which thing you would have to be nothing<note n="*" place="margin">Pa. 13. p. 14.</note>; for in ſpeaking of the <hi>ordinances of the common-wealth,</hi> you include them all, and ſo you would inferre that what an Antichriſtian mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry doth, if it be done by a falſe <hi>power,</hi> the action (whether it be <hi>baptiſme,</hi> or any other thing) it is falſe: but this your ground will not hold. For the <hi>Kings</hi> lawfull acts are reall, and ſubſtantiall, though the diſpenſation of the ſame (in reſpect of the party diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing) be contrary to his mind and will. As if the King command that none in his Realme ſhall marrie perſons together, but the Chriſtian Magiſtrates. But if the Prieſts do the ſame contrary to the Kings com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, ſhall we ſay the Parties are not married, and that the marriage is falſe and counterfeit? this I conceive you will not affirme<note n="*" place="margin">For then their children begotten (in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eſtate) are baſtards.</note> So your former ground being groundleſſe, your compariſon is fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volous.</p>
            <p>And conſidering that <hi>Gods</hi> ordinance of <hi>circumciſion</hi> was reall and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:155922:14"/> effectuall, though adminiſtred by a <hi>falſe power,</hi> you cannot ſay that it was none of <hi>Gods ordinance,</hi> for then they ſhould have been <hi>circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed</hi> again: ſo the like may be ſaid concerning <hi>baptiſme.</hi> Therefore your other compariſon and application<note n="*" place="margin">Pa. 14. at l 26</note> [in this caſe] about <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres rods,</hi> &amp;c. (2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.9. <hi>Exod.</hi> 7.10. <hi>ver.</hi> 11.12.) is of no weight, but rather a wreſting of the words of the <hi>Scripture,</hi> for you can gather no ſuch concluſion out of <hi>Pauls</hi> words, neither by any part of the <hi>Scripture</hi> it ſelf, or neceſſarie conſequence; for though theſe <hi>Antichriſtians</hi> (in oppoſing the truth) are like <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres,</hi> yet becauſe they draw <hi>neer unto God</hi> with their mouthes, (and their hearts farre from him) they are rather like the <hi>Apoſtate Iſraelites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For which <hi>Papiſt</hi> (of the groſſeſt of them) will deny <hi>verbally</hi> that <hi>Chriſt is come in the fleſh,</hi> that <hi>there are three perſons in the Trinity;</hi> &amp;c. ſo farre are they from denying it, that they abhorre thoſe that ſay to the contrary, and are readie to burne them with fire and fagot. Such a kind of zeal have they for him whom they know not rightly, but in their ſuperſtitious works denie him: And (by your own confeſſion<note n="**" place="margin">Pa. 15. l. 20.</note>) the Church of England doth in their nineteenth Article <hi>profeſſe,</hi> that <hi>the viſible Church of Chriſt conſiſteth of faithfull men, &amp;c.</hi> this is a reall truth; And yet theſe perſons (I ſay) do <hi>deny Chriſt,</hi> becauſe they ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit not unto him as he is <hi>Prophet, Prieſt,</hi> and <hi>King.</hi> And yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding we will not ſay but that theſe <hi>Apoſtaticall</hi> perſons have <hi>baptiſme,</hi> and as much <hi>right</hi> unto it, and <hi>power</hi> and authoritie to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter it, as the <hi>Apoſtates</hi> of old had to receive and adminiſter <hi>cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion.</hi> But the Temple, and the Altar, and the worſhippers muſt be meaſured, when the Court which is without (by Gods command) muſt be left out, and not meaſured, becauſe it was given to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.1, 2.<note n="***" place="margin">Chriſtian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, underſtand that whereas Mr. <hi>A.R.</hi> hath (in his treatiſe of Baptiſme, p. 12. to 22. p. 31.32.) ſpoken againſt the power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, and office of mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, which the man of ſin hath given to the Miniſters of Antichriſt, I contradict him not in this, but do judge them (in the ſame viſible eſtate) as <hi>Ieroboams</hi> apoſtaticall prieſts were, though they have baptiſme as the other had circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> (you<note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 23. to p. 24. lin 4.</note> ſay) <hi>the ground from which baptiſme is there admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, is the repentance and faith of the ſureties;</hi> the evidence whereof you bring out of the <hi>Catechiſme: where they declare, that repentance and faith is required to baptiſme; and that the infants performe it by the ſureties, who take upon them to anſwer for the infants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That <hi>repentance</hi> and <hi>faith</hi> is required to <hi>baptiſme</hi> is true; but ſeeing the <hi>ſureties</hi> are not able to perform it for themſelves, much leſſe can they do it for others; It is not <hi>Noah, Daniel,</hi> or <hi>Job</hi> that can ſave any ſinner from <hi>Gods</hi> wrath<note n="a" place="margin">Ezek. 14.14</note>; <hi>the righteous are ſcarcely ſaved</hi> themſelves<note n="b" place="margin">1. Pet 4.18.</note>; how then ſhall the wicked undertake, ſo preſumptuouſly
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:155922:15"/> to anſwer for any, eſpecially for thoſe whom <hi>God</hi> (in his revealed will) hath made no promiſe to ſave; yet though the members of the <hi>Church of England</hi> do preſume ſo farre, it doth not make a nullitie of the ordinance, no more then the Philiſtines preſumption in ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Arke of God<note n="c" place="margin">1. Sam. 4.10, 11. and 5.1.</note>, or the men of Bethſhemoſh their looking therein<note n="d" place="margin">&amp; 6.19.</note>, made it to be no Ark of God; neither doth mens traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons deſtroy Gods inſtitutions; for Gods pillars and poſts are ſtill his own, though Idolaters do ſet theirs thereby<note n="e" place="margin">Ezek. 43.8.</note>.</p>
            <p>But though ſome in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> do <hi>baptiſe</hi> by <hi>ſureties,</hi> (which they commonly call <hi>godfathers</hi> and <hi>godmothers</hi>) yet others ſee it to be <hi>vaine</hi> and <hi>popiſh,</hi> and do <hi>baptiſe</hi> their <hi>children</hi> without them, theſe [in reſpect of the ground which you have here inſtanced] you cannot object againſt.</p>
            <p>Now, the <hi>ground</hi> wherefore the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> doth adminiſter <hi>baptiſme,</hi> is taken out of <hi>Gods Word;</hi> (at leaſt pretended (by them) ſo to be) how <hi>Chriſt</hi> declared that <hi>little children belong to the kingdom of God; and he took them up in his arms, &amp; laid his hands upon them and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them, &amp;c. yea from the very inſtitution of Jeſus Chriſt unto his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> Matth. 28.19. Mark. 16.16. this I ſay (though it be the ground whereby they adminiſter <hi>baptiſme,</hi> as (peradventure) the <hi>ground</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtates</hi> of <hi>Iſrael circumciſing,</hi> was taken from the commiſſion of <hi>God</hi> given to <hi>Abraham</hi>) yet theſe <hi>Idolaters</hi> (like the <hi>Apoſtate Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites</hi>) are ſacralegious abuſers of this holy inſtitution of God.</p>
            <p>Thus having anſwered directly to your foure particulars, which you have brought againſt the baptiſme in the Church of England; I now proceed to anſwer your fifth and laſt particular; (to wit) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſubjects which you treated of, in your firſt particular, where you paſſed from the end to the ſubject.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 24.</note>THe <hi>ſubjects</hi> (ſay you) on which baptiſme is there adminiſtred are infants.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, that you have omitted a materiall word, for you ſhould have ſaid the <hi>infants</hi> of <hi>[Idolaters]</hi> but when you ſpeake of <hi>infants</hi> [in generall] without denoting what ſort of <hi>infants</hi> you mean; you ſpeak in the aire!</p>
            <p>But you grant that <hi>the Scripture holdeth forth, that diſciples</hi> (or <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers) onely are to be baptiſed;</hi> which is really my judgement, that onely <hi>beleevers</hi> (or diſciples) are to be <hi>baptiſed,</hi> as formerly they were to be <hi>circumciſed;</hi> and as <hi>Abraham</hi> himſelf had no command to <hi>circumciſe</hi> all <hi>nations,</hi> or <hi>ſeeds,</hi> (or any <hi>apoſtate</hi> whatſoever, though
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:155922:15"/> the off-ſpring of his body) but thoſe that were the <hi>ſeed</hi> in <hi>covenant</hi> with <hi>God</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 7.14.</note>, ſo the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> had no warrant to <hi>baptiſe</hi> any other, but <hi>beleeving men and women,</hi> and their <hi>holy ſeed;</hi> according to the great commiſſion of our bleſſed Saviour, where all nations were command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be baptiſed, onely upon this condition, that they ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come diſciples, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.16. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.38. And I grant with you, <hi>that to be a diſciple of Chriſt is to abide in him, and to continue in his words,</hi> Joh. 8.31. <hi>ſuch are Chriſts diſciples indeed, and are made free by Chriſt</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Joh 8.36.</note>; <hi>ſuch as beare the croſſe, and come after Chriſt, forſaking all that they have;</hi> But know this, that <hi>free Justification</hi> cometh not by any act of our own, but by the <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Christ,</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted unto us<note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 63.3.5 &amp; 53.10, 11, 12. Rom. 3.6. Rev. 1.5. &amp; 5.3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10.</note>. And therefore holy <hi>infants</hi> may be ſaid in one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to do all theſe things; <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf hath declared, that they receive the <hi>kingdome</hi> of God; and ſuch <hi>holy infants</hi> are his <hi>diſciples</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed; ſuch have born the <hi>croſſe</hi> divers times, ſuffering with their holy parents, for the ſame cauſe; and they reſiſt not the will of God in any thing; theſe are not all infants, but onely the infants of beleeving pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, whom we ought to judge as righteous, and as holy (till they manifeſt otherwiſe) as any other Saint on earth, though he profeſſe great things; theſe are thoſe heavenly creatures, to whom the <hi>Goſpel</hi> ought be applyed though they are uncapable to receive it <hi>actually;</hi> yea when the Goſpel is verbally applyed to the <hi>parents,</hi> their <hi>infants</hi> are not exempted, but received, according to Chriſts words unto <hi>Zacheus, To day is ſalvation come to this houſe, for as much as he alſo is the ſonne of Abraham</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Luk. 19.9.</note>. Chriſt hath promiſed life to thoſe that chuſe life, and alſo to their infants; and therefore the ſame infants have <hi>faith</hi> imputatively, for he that <hi>beleeveth not, ſhall be damned.</hi> So that it appeareth, that ſalvation cometh not but by faith in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>For as much then as the Scripture is ſo clear, that theſe holy <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants</hi> are <hi>ſaved,</hi> and ſeeing that <hi>ſalvation</hi> cometh not without <hi>repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance</hi> and <hi>faith:</hi> It is too much preſumption to ſay, that <hi>infants</hi> are deſtitute of <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>repentance;</hi> though all the men in the world would grant it.</p>
            <p>But I do wonder what is the maine ground that doth drive you, or, the greateſt reaſon (or conceit) that doth draw you ſo to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine concerning <hi>infants</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 25.</note>, as if they were deſtitute of the heavenly gifts and graces of <hi>Gods</hi> Spirit; Is it becauſe they cannot verbally expreſſe (or actually perform) ſuch things, as thoſe of riper yeers can do? If this be your greateſt reaſon, it will not beare down the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:155922:16"/> leaſt weight in the ballance of Gods ſanctuary; as may eaſily ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare.</p>
            <p>But though <hi>baptiſme</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> be adminiſtred up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the wrong <hi>ſubjects</hi> (namely the ſeed of Idolaters) and though <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life</hi> be ſought and promiſed by them another way then <hi>God</hi> hath appointed; yet to affirm, that becauſe ſome infants are not meet ſubjects of baptiſme, that therefore no infants are, is a ſaying found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the ſands, and fetched out of the fond fictions of mens brains, and not from the word of <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your beſt way had been this, to have ſearched into the <hi>records</hi> of <hi>holy Scripture,</hi> and obſerved the nature of the ordinance of <hi>circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion,</hi> and compared the ſame ſigne<note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 17.13.</note> and ſeale<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 4.11.</note> of righteouſneſſe with <hi>baptiſme</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Col. 2.11, 12.</note>, and ſo to have found out the <hi>equivolence</hi> which the one hath with the other, and then you ſhould have examined whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>circumciſion</hi> of <hi>Apoſtate Infants</hi> were according to the will of <hi>God,</hi> and if it were not, whether they were commanded (by the Lord) at their returning, to be <hi>circumciſed</hi> again; If it had been ſo, then you might have had <hi>ground</hi> to have beaten down the <hi>baptiſme,</hi> which is received in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England:</hi> but this is not the way you take; but inſtead of this you ſhoot at <hi>rovers;</hi> not keeping to the matter in hand. And till it can be proved that the <hi>circumciſion</hi> of <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants</hi> was none of the Lords <hi>circumciſion,</hi> I muſt ſtill ſay, that the <hi>bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme</hi> of <hi>Infants</hi> is the <hi>Lords baptiſme;</hi> wherefore <hi>ſtand to your cauſe, and bring forth your ſtrong reaſons.</hi> For as yet your reaſons are verie weak, though you conceive you have brought them to <hi>ſuch an iſſue, that,</hi> you ſay<note n="*" place="margin">Pa. 26.</note>, <hi>you ſhall now proceed no further therein:</hi> yet (I ſay) except you can make void the <hi>covenant</hi> of <hi>Abraham</hi> ſo much, that it doth not appertain to the <hi>infants</hi> of beleeving parents, as well as to the parents themſelves, and that the application of the Goſpel ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaineth not to them alſo, and that the generall commiſſion of <hi>Chriſt</hi> includeth not <hi>infants,</hi> [which you can never do while the world ſtands, ſeeing the Scripture (in this point) is ſo clear againſt you] I muſt ſtill ſay, that the <hi>baptiſme</hi> of ſuch <hi>infants</hi> is lawfull, and warrantable; yea for as much as it was acted by <hi>God</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">1. Cor. 10 2</note>, and <hi>inſtituted</hi> by <hi>Chriſt</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 28.19 M rk. 16.16.</note>, it ought to be practiſed by his <hi>Saints,</hi> perpetually to the end of the <hi>world</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 28.20.</note>; and the further you go on in gain-ſaying this truth <hi>the greater is your ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For, all unbaptiſed perſons to whom the application of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> doth appertain, are expreſly commanded (by <hi>Chriſt</hi>) to be <hi>baptiſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:155922:16"/>
            <p>But the application of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> appertaineth to the <hi>infants</hi> of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving parents.</p>
            <p>Therefore <hi>all ſuch infants (if they be not alreadie baptiſed) are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly commanded (by Chriſt) to be baptiſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt part of this argument is proved from <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.16.</p>
            <p>The ſecond, namely, that the application of the Goſpel apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth to theſe infants is proved.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By the <hi>covenant</hi> of <hi>Abraham,</hi> which was a covenant of life,<note place="margin">Gen. 17.7.</note> ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally made with <hi>Gods viſible Church</hi> both <hi>young</hi> and <hi>old.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, by the teſtimony of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that they are part of the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture of his Fathers <hi>kingdome</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Mar. 10.13.14.</note>, and theſe <hi>veſſels</hi> though they be but of <hi>[ſmall]</hi> quantitie<note n="e" place="margin">Iſa. 22.24.</note>, yet they are <hi>ſpiritually holy,</hi> and therefore have a right to <hi>baptiſme,</hi> the <hi>ſigne</hi> and <hi>ſeale</hi> of the <hi>righteouſneſſe of faith,</hi> (as really) as the <hi>infants</hi> of the <hi>beleeving Hebrews</hi> had right to <hi>circumciſion</hi> the <hi>ſigne</hi> and <hi>ſeal of the ſame righteouſneſſe of faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore this adminiſtring or <hi>baptiſme</hi> upon ſuch holy <hi>infants,</hi> doth not prevent the adminiſtring of <hi>baptiſme</hi> upon <hi>diſciples</hi> (or <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers</hi>) as you falſly ſpeak<note n="*" place="margin">Pa. 27.</note>.</p>
            <p>For ſeeing the <hi>infants</hi> of <hi>beleevers</hi> are not placed among <hi>dogs,</hi> and <hi>whoremongers</hi> without, they are within the new Jeruſalem, and have right to the <hi>holy Citie,</hi> and the priviledges thereof<note n="f" place="margin">Rev. 22.14.15.</note>. For <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> (who <hi>is yeſterday, to day, and the ſame for ever,</hi> Hebr. 13 8.) never gave them ſuch a diſmiſſi n, that they ſhould not be members of his viſible <hi>Church,</hi> as heretofore they have been, (<hi>Exod.</hi> 12.48.) but rather he hath confirmed them therein, (<hi>Jer.</hi> 30.20.) for <hi>all the promiſes of God are yea, and Amen, in Chriſt.</hi> 2 Cor. 1 20.</p>
            <p>Therefo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, I deſire rather to magnifie the mighty power of <hi>God</hi> by which the <hi>infants</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were <hi>baptiſed</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">1 Cor. 10 1 2.</note> in the dayes of <hi>Moſes,</hi> (before the Law was given on mount Sinai<note n="h" place="margin">Joh. 7.22.</note>) then deny them <hi>bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm</hi> now in the dayes of the <hi>M ſſias,</hi> or call the <hi>baptiſm</hi> of ſuch <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> a device of mans braine, and no <hi>baptiſme</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as you have here preſumptuouſly (or (at leaſt) ignorantly) done<note n="*" place="margin">Pa 28.</note>, you plead<note n="i" place="margin">Pa. 28 li. 15 16.</note> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>baptiſing</hi> of infants deſtitute of faith.</p>
            <p>But thoſe <hi>infants</hi> are the infants of <hi>idolatrous parents,</hi> whom we are not to name among the living in Je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſalem<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſa. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> till either one or both of their <hi>parents</hi> repe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t, or till they renounce their <hi>parents ſinne,</hi> according to that in <hi>Ez k</hi> 18 14.17. And the <hi>baptiſing</hi> of thoſe <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants</hi> I do not allow of, but would have them to be put by; but ſome of them being <hi>baptiſed</hi> (though not aright) ſhall we ſay that that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:155922:17"/> 
               <hi>baptiſme</hi> is no <hi>baptiſme,</hi> or that it is another <hi>baptiſme</hi> then the <hi>baptiſme</hi> of <hi>beleevers;</hi> no ſurely, there is no more externall <hi>baptiſmes</hi> of water, then there were externall <hi>circumciſions.</hi> Now if you can prove, that there were (appointed by God) divers externall <hi>circumciſions,</hi> both in reſpect of the nature, end, and uſe therof, (one <hi>circumciſion</hi> for <hi>infants,</hi> another for elder perſons) and that the <hi>circumciſion</hi> of <hi>infants</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented the <hi>circumciſion</hi> of <hi>Beleevers;</hi> then you may with more colour of truth ſay, that the <hi>baptiſme</hi> of <hi>infants</hi> preventeth the <hi>baptiſme</hi> of <hi>beleevers,</hi> and make the <hi>baptiſme</hi> of <hi>infants</hi> a different thing from it, which thing you can never do.</p>
            <p>But peradventure you will ſay, (by <hi>infants</hi> here) you meane the <hi>infants</hi> of <hi>wicked</hi> and <hi>idolatrous parents,</hi> and not the <hi>infants</hi> of the <hi>faithfull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, that then you ſhould have ſo expreſſed; But I would have you to mind, that though the act of <hi>baptiſing idolaters</hi> be different from the <hi>[baptiſing]</hi> of true <hi>Chriſtians</hi> (in reſpect of the <hi>manner, effect,</hi> and application thereof) yet the <hi>[baptiſme]</hi> is one and the ſame, even as the circumciſing of the <hi>apoſtate Jews,</hi> and of thoſe that were not <hi>Apoſtates,</hi> did not argue but that the <hi>circumciſion</hi> was one and the ſame, but differed in the <hi>manner</hi> of adminiſtration, and in the application thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pa. 28. lin. 19. to lin. 28.</note>Whereas you ſay, that <hi>the baptiſme of infants as it is by authoritie or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained in this kingdome, doth thus farre prevent the baptiſing of beleevers, that hereby no native can be baptiſed upon faith, ſeeing all are to be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in their infancie, when they are deſtitute of faith: wherefore if all other Kingdoms and Nations did the ſame, then the commandment of Chriſt, for the baptiſme of diſciples (or beleevers) would be quite pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, and deſtroyed out of the whole world, as well as it is out of this Kingdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, that though the natives <hi>infants</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> be not <hi>baptiſed</hi> upon their <hi>faith;</hi> becauſe <hi>Idolaters</hi> have no <hi>faith</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 22.15.</note>; yet if any do return out of that <hi>Apoſtaſie,</hi> they are not to be <hi>baptiſed</hi> again, no more then the penitent <hi>apoſtate Iſraelites</hi> were <hi>circumciſed</hi> again; becauſe (<hi>God</hi> having purged the evill of the <hi>manner</hi> of admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring his ordinance) the ordinance is really accounted with <hi>God,</hi> (and ought ſo to be eſteemed of his <hi>Saints</hi>) as done upon a right <hi>ſubject.</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, ſee Mr. <hi>Henry Barrow</hi> [a Martyr in Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beths</hi> time] his diſcovery, (pa. 114. and ſo forth to the end of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) where he handleth this particular point at large.</note>.</p>
            <p>And though we had no right to <hi>baptiſme</hi> (as we ſtood) in that eſtate, but wickedly uſurped the ſame, yet being come out of <hi>Babel,</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:155922:17"/> that which is <hi>Gods,</hi> we have a right unto; although we received the ſame before we ſeparated from <hi>Babel;</hi> Even ſo the <hi>Apostates</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> (in their <hi>apoſtaſie</hi>) had no right to the <hi>circumciſion</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 50.16. Hoſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.2, 3, 4. Jer. 9.25, 26.</note> they received in that <hi>apoſtaſie,</hi> but when any of them returned to <hi>Judah</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">1. Chron 30.13.</note>, they were not commanded to be <hi>circumciſed</hi> againe, becauſe they then had a right to that <hi>circumciſion</hi> which they had formerly received in that <hi>idolatrous way</hi> in which they had walked.</p>
            <p>Even as a man which ſtealeth goods from the owner thereof, hath no right unto them; but if he bring the ſame back to the owner, and the owner give him that which he formerly ſtole<note n="*" place="margin">The ſtealing of a thing doth not alter the property there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, or make the thing to be nothing.</note>, then he hath a right unto them.</p>
            <p>So when we were in the <hi>idolatrous aſſemblies,</hi> we were <hi>run-awayes,</hi> and <hi>apoſtates</hi> from <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>theeves</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> like <hi>Jeroboam</hi> and his crue, but when we returned, we came and tendered to <hi>God</hi> that which we had ſtollen from him; even as the penitent <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did their <hi>cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion;</hi> and as <hi>God</hi> did not command them to be <hi>circumciſed</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; no more hath he commanded us to be <hi>baptiſed</hi> again; but is graciouſly pleaſed to beſtow upon us thoſe falſe gotten goods, which we unjuſtly did reſet, and receive, from the hand of our old mother,<note place="margin">Prov. 9.17. Rev. 9 21.</note> that <hi>whore</hi> of <hi>Babylon,</hi> which ſtole them from <hi>God:</hi> who ordinarily doth mixe her own traditions with <hi>Gods,</hi> to make her own ware to paſſe in ſale.</p>
            <p>Whereas you ſay, that <hi>the baptiſme of diſciples (or beleevers) is out of this kingdome of England:</hi> Indeed I hope it is not ſo. For there are a number of <hi>baptiſed beleevers</hi> who do <hi>baptiſe</hi> their <hi>infants,</hi> and ſo long as they ſo do, the ordinance of <hi>baptiſing diſciples</hi> (or <hi>beleevers</hi>) will not out of the land where they are now, or whereſoever (by <hi>Gods</hi> providence) they ſhall be caſt.</p>
            <p>And you ſhould mind that the <hi>baptiſme</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> appertaineth to <hi>beleevers,</hi> therefore, it is theirs properly; and though <hi>idolaters</hi> (by Gods permiſſion) ſacraligiouſly abuſe it, yet they do not deſtroy it, but rather deſtroy themſelves with it, as the <hi>Philiſtines</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1. Sam. 5.9, 10.</note> in retaining the <hi>Arke.</hi> But I could wiſh that you would put a diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction between <hi>[baptiſme]</hi> and <hi>baptiſing,</hi> the manner of <hi>baptiſing</hi> being theirs, but the <hi>baptiſme</hi> properly <hi>Gods;</hi> appertaining to his <hi>Church,</hi> as well as the outward <hi>court</hi> (in the Law) appertained to the <hi>Temple</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2. Chron. 4.9</note>.</p>
            <p>Further (you ſay) <hi>that if any ſhall here object and ſay, the diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the evill of this forme of baptiſing is needleſſe, ſeeing divers perſons ſee it already to be ſo frivolous and naught, that they much diſlike it, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:155922:18"/> will not have their children baptiſed with godfathers, but upon other grounds, namely, from the covenant made with beleevers, and their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, upon which ground alſo, they of the ſeparation uſe to baptiſe their children, wherefore their arguments ſhould have been likewiſe anſwered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this you anſwer:</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Although ſome few ſee this forme of baptiſing to be ſinfull and naught, yet what is this to the reſt of the whole Nation, who yet make con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of that Idol to this day?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Although they of the ſeparation, and ſome others, do mend the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (as they thinke) in the baptiſing of their children otherwiſe, and upon other grounds, yet what is all this to their own baptiſme, being naught by their own confeſſion; and a nullitie alſo, even from their own grounds: for they grant, that no children ſave onely beleevers children, are in the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, or have right to baptiſme; then moſt of themſelves had no right to baptiſme, their parents (by their own acknowledgement) being ungodly: whence it will follow, that they themſelves being baptiſed in their infancy, had not the baptiſme of Chriſt, and ſo by conſequence are yet unbaptiſed perſons: Thus is their own baptiſme clearly made void from their own grounds, and how then can their children be now baptiſed in the right of ſuch parents, who are yet unbaptiſed themſelves?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To all which I reply: That though I hold the diſcovering of the evill <hi>forme</hi> of <hi>baptiſing</hi> to be needfull, yet I diſlike your evill proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in the diſcovery thereof.</p>
            <p>But whereas you ſpeake of the forme of <hi>baptiſing,</hi> and the forme of <hi>baptiſme</hi> both in the objection<note n="a" place="margin">Pa 28. l. 33.34.</note> and the anſwer which you make<note n="b" place="margin">P 29 l. 6</note>, I ſuppoſe, you intend the ſet form for <hi>baptiſing,</hi> mentioned in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer Book, and this (I conceive) is the <hi>Idol,</hi> which you ſay<note n="c" place="margin">li. 8 9.</note>, many make conſcience of to this day; and if this be your meaning, I will not oppoſe you, becauſe I am of that mind, and ſo are the beſt informed <hi>Chriſtians</hi> that the <hi>Common Prayer Book</hi> is vaine and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh, and meeter for <hi>[Babels brats]</hi> then for <hi>[Simons babes],</hi> and better beſeeming time-ſerving <hi>[Maſſe-mongers]</hi> to be occupied there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, then the faithfull, laborious, and painfull <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereas you ſay, <hi>the ſeperation and ſome others do mend the matter (as they thinke) in the baptiſing of their children otherwiſe, and upon other grounds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer. If by the ſeparation you meane thoſe that are come out of <hi>Babel,</hi> (I ſay) I know none (either <hi>young</hi> or <hi>old</hi>) that
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:155922:18"/> have right to <hi>baptiſme</hi> in <hi>Babel,</hi> or if they walk in any of the ſinnes of <hi>Babel,</hi> and will not be reclaimed; they have no right to any of <hi>Gods ordinances,</hi> becauſe they are not <hi>viſible Saints.</hi> And therefore they cannot have ſuch <hi>grounds</hi> for <hi>baptiſing</hi> their <hi>infants,</hi> as the <hi>Saints</hi> have for <hi>baptiſing</hi> theirs: for thoſe that are out of <hi>covenant</hi> themſelves, as they cannot lawfully apply the <hi>covenant</hi> to their ſeed, (nor to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) no more can they apply the <hi>ſeal</hi> of the <hi>Covenant;</hi> neither is it lawfull for them to <hi>baptiſe</hi> any at all, whether <hi>beleevers</hi> or <hi>unbelee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,</hi> for it is <hi>ſacriledge</hi> for any that are not <hi>viſible Saints</hi> to admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter or partake of any of <hi>Gods ordinances.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas you ask the ſeparation (and theſe <hi>ſome others) what all this is to their own baptiſme, which</hi> (ſay you) <hi>is naught by their own confeſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here I ſuppoſe you do not take along with you the diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the <hi>ſeperation;</hi> for we ſay that when we were in <hi>Babylon,</hi> the <hi>baptiſme</hi> we received was not properly ours, but <hi>Gods baptiſme,</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining onely to <hi>viſible Saints.</hi> And though we hold the <hi>manner</hi> of <hi>[baptiſing]</hi> to be <hi>naught,</hi> yet the <hi>[baptiſme]</hi> in it ſelf <hi>we</hi> affirm, and have proved (and will ſtill further prove upon occaſion) that it is <hi>good;</hi> but the <hi>baptiſme</hi> of the holy Infants of beleevers adminiſtred up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them out of <hi>Babel,</hi> we hold to be good in every reſpect, and that it hath no need of any purgation. And I ſuppoſe you alledge no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing againſt the <hi>baptiſme</hi> we adminiſter now, but onely the mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the <hi>ſubject</hi> (which you account in no better an eſtate then a <hi>heathen.</hi>) And becauſe we have not ſuch a multiplication of the <hi>element</hi> as may dip a man in, <hi>all</hi> over.</p>
            <p>As for thoſe <hi>ſome others</hi> beſides <hi>Separates,</hi> which, you alſo ſay, do mend the matter, I know not who they be, if they are not ſeparated from the unclean thing, they are unclean; and how do they mend the matter, that are not amended themſelves?</p>
            <p>We do not ſay, that <hi>no children, ſave onely beleevers children, are in the covenant, or have right to Baptiſme;</hi> you here miſtake us (or elſe miſtake your ſelf) for we affirm that ſome <hi>unbeleevers children</hi> are in the <hi>covenant,</hi> though their <hi>parents</hi> are out of the <hi>covenant;</hi> and we alſo hold, that ſome <hi>beleevers children</hi> are out of the <hi>covenant,</hi> though their parents are in the <hi>covenant;</hi> but ſuch of their <hi>children</hi> as are <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants,</hi> and (alſo ſuch of yeers) which depart not from the ſteps of their righteous <hi>parents</hi>) we judge to be in the <hi>covenant;</hi> Now, I ſay, if by <hi>children</hi> you mean <hi>infants,</hi> then we ſtill affirm, that all the <hi>chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:155922:19"/> of unbeleevers [in their <hi>infancie</hi>] are out of the <hi>covenant,</hi> (ſo far as men can judge) and have no right to <hi>baptiſme,</hi> [their parents be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ungodly.]</p>
            <p>For how can the infants be ſaid to be godly, in viſibilitie, [either by action, or imputation] ſo long as their parents are viſible idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, either perſonally, or ſtatively: Surely, where the guilt of <hi>originall ſinne</hi> is not to be judged to be <hi>imputatively</hi> done away by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the viſible <hi>ſeal</hi> of the <hi>forgiveneſſe</hi> of that <hi>ſinne</hi> ought not to be applyed, but their <hi>guilt</hi> of <hi>originall ſinne</hi> is not [in Gods <hi>revealed</hi> will] decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red (and therefore is not of us to be judged) to be imputatively done away by Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Therefore <hi>baptiſme</hi> (which is the viſible ſeal of the <hi>forgiveneſſe</hi> of that <hi>ſinne,</hi>) ought not to be applyed unto ſuch perſons.</p>
            <p>And though we affirm, that we had no right to <hi>baptiſme</hi> in the ſtate of <hi>Apoſtaſie,</hi> (our <hi>parents</hi> being then Antichriſtians) yet it will not follow (as you would inferre) that we had not the <hi>baptiſme</hi> of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> neither by our own grounds, nor from any ground you have, or (I ſuppoſe) can alledge againſt the ſame; And therefore there is no place for you to build any juſt <hi>conſequence</hi> that we are <hi>unbaptiſed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons;</hi> yea though you upon this unneceſſarie <hi>conſequence</hi> build an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, that our own <hi>baptiſme is clearly made void even from</hi> our <hi>own grounds;</hi> and upon this conceit of yours, you ask <hi>how then can their children be now baptiſed in the right of ſuch parents, who are yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſed themſelves?</hi> and ſo you take for granted, that which you cannot prove. For I think in this particular concerning the baptiſme of ſuch infants, you may ſeek your oppoſite among the <hi>Babylonians,</hi> for I conceive no Seperate will in this oppoſe you.</p>
            <p>But (you ſay) <hi>the grounds which Seperates and others do urge for the baptiſing of Infants, ſhall be further examined and anſwered (if God will) in anothe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Treatiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, that there ſhall be a Reply made thereunto with all ſpeed (God willing) in another Treatiſe.</p>
            <p>Next you adde, that if any ſhall think it ſtrange and unlikely, that all the godlieſt Divines, and beſt Churches, ſhould be thus deceived in this point of Baptiſme for ſo many yeers together.</p>
            <p>Let them conſider (ſay you) that all Chriſtendome (except here and there one, or ſome few, or no conſiderable number) was ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up in groſſe Poperie for many hundred yeers before <hi>Luthers</hi> time, which was not untill about 100 yeers agone.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:155922:19"/>
            <p>To which I anſwer, that all this is nothing at all to the point, for the <hi>apoſtaſie</hi> of Iſrael was for many hundred yeers; and yet the <hi>Saints,</hi> I ſuppoſe, did not doubt but the <hi>Apoſtates</hi> were deceived in the point of <hi>circumciſion;</hi> howbeit not ſimply in circumciſing, or in circumciſing of Infants, (for that was the ordinance of God) but in <hi>circumciſing</hi> in <hi>apoſtaſie,</hi> and impoſing the <hi>ſigne</hi> upon <hi>Apoſtates,</hi> and their <hi>apoſtate ſeed, Therefore</hi> (the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaith unto God) <hi>thou haſt forſaken thy people, the houſe of Jacob: becauſe they are repleniſhed from the Eaſt, and are ſouthſayers like the Philiſtines, and pleaſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the children of ſtrangers.</hi> Iſa. 2. So theſe <hi>Apoſtates</hi> are not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived (ſimply) in the act of <hi>baptiſing,</hi> or in adminiſtring it upon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants (onely as they are infants) but becauſe they <hi>baptiſe</hi> in that <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous</hi> and <hi>Apoſtate ſtate,</hi> and adminiſter the <hi>ſigne</hi> upon the <hi>infants</hi> of <hi>ungodly parents.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In comparing the Baptiſme of Infants with the abominable hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchy, you foulely miſſe, (eſpecially if you meane the infants of godly parents;) you might as well have ſaid, that the circumciſion of Infants was as bad as <hi>Jeroboams</hi> hierarchy which he made of the loweſt of the people<note n="a" place="margin">1. King. 13.33, 34</note>. But conſidering that the circumciſion of holy Infants was the ſame ſigne<note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 17.11.</note> and ſeal<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 4.11.</note> of the righteouſneſſe of faith which <hi>Abraham</hi> had; and conſidering that baptiſme is come in the ſtead of it, and that it is no leſſe generall then circumciſion, nor infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour thereunto<note n="d" place="margin">Col. 2.11, 12.</note>, you may perceive that the baptiſme of Infants is an ordinance from heaven.</p>
            <p>But the hierarchy are the armie of Locuſts, which came from hell, and were hatched in the [ſmoke] of the bottomles pit<note n="e" place="margin">Rev. 9.3.</note>, which ſmoke is ſomewhat like to Biſhop <hi>Hals</hi> foggie Divinitie, which you have ſet down<note n="*" place="margin">Pa. 30. at li. 8.</note> for <hi>memorandum.</hi> In whoſe judgement (you ſay) the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme of Infants hath leſſe warrant, then the hierarchy; but this his erronious judgement, will ſtand you in no ſtead, neither will his chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge<note n="*" place="margin">Lin. 27. 28, 29, 30.</note> nor the judgement of any other (though never ſo much no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) avail you any thing at all, in this your oppoſition of the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme of the infants of beleevers. Neither can <hi>Biſhop Hall</hi> on the <hi>one ſide,</hi> nor you on the <hi>other ſide,</hi> (with all the help you can get) over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the baptiſme of Infants; for all your <hi>words</hi> without the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of Scripture is but <hi>wind;</hi> for it is preſumption (or ignorance at the beſt) in <hi>Biſhop Hall</hi> and you: ſo to ſpeak concerning <hi>Infants bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme,</hi> as if the Scripture owned it not.</p>
            <p>But all which you have here ſaid doth not overthrow our <hi>baptiſme</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:155922:20"/> which we received in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> for if <hi>Apoſtates</hi> ſhould weare out <hi>Gods ordinance</hi> of <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> any more then the <hi>Apoſtates</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> did weare out the <hi>ordinance</hi> of <hi>circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion</hi> in the time of <hi>Iſraels Apoſtaſie</hi> (before Chriſt was mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted in the fleſh) it would argue a great weakneſſe, and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as if he were not ſo faithfull in his houſe as <hi>Moſes,</hi> or as if <hi>Baptiſme</hi> were of ſmaller value, and ſooner worne out then <hi>circumciſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But you (in the entrance of your Treatiſe) have granted it to be a great ordinance of the New Teſtament. To which I further adde for concluſion, that as circumciſion was not worn out, but was ſo permanent that it remained till <hi>Chriſts firſt coming,</hi> and till he took away the beggerly rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the old Covenant: ſo baptiſme hath not nor ſhall not be worne out or taken away, but remaine as permanent, till <hi>Chriſt</hi> come to give us the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of all his <hi>ordinances;</hi> the <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment</hi> of all his <hi>promiſes,</hi> the <hi>enjoyment</hi> of that <hi>immortall</hi> and <hi>unchangeable inheritance</hi> which ſhall never be worne out, or taken away, but remaine from <hi>everlaſting</hi> to <hi>everlaſting.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:155922:20"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>PAg. 12. lin. 7. for Chriſts, read, Chriſt. li. 15. leave out theſe words, that the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> ſo did <hi>baptiſe.</hi> p. 13. l 8. in the Marg. for Pſal. 16.17, r. Pſal. 77.16.17.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
